<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catalogue of the damages for which the English demand reparation from the United-Netherlands as also a list of the damages, actions, and pretenses for which those of the United-Netherlands demand reparation and satisfaction from the English, together with the answer of the English, subjoyn'd to the several and respective points of their demands.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11680688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11680688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 485:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catalogue of the damages for which the English demand reparation from the United-Netherlands as also a list of the damages, actions, and pretenses for which those of the United-Netherlands demand reparation and satisfaction from the English, together with the answer of the English, subjoyn'd to the several and respective points of their demands.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerns the English and Dutch East India Companies.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:48101:1"/>
            <p>Let this CATALOGUE and LIST of <hi>DAMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GES</hi> be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1. 1664</date>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48101:1"/>
            <p>A CATALOGUE OF THE DAMAGES FOR WHICH THE ENGLISH Demand REPARATION from the United-Netherlands. AS ALSO A <hi>LIST</hi> of the <hi>DAMAGES, ACTIONS,</hi> and <hi>PRETENSES</hi> for which Thoſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITED-NETHER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LANDS</hi> demand <hi>Reparation</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> from the <hi>ENGLISH.</hi> TOGETHER WITH The <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> ſubjoyn'd to the Several and Reſpective Points of Their <hi>Demands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48101:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Practices</hi> of our <hi>Neighbours</hi> the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> towards his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and his <hi>Subjects,</hi> have been ſo <hi>notorious,</hi> both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,</hi> in <hi>Private</hi> and in <hi>Publique,</hi> in their <hi>Prints, Writings,</hi> and <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> that the whole world is ſufficiently enform'd how great a part they have made it of their buſineſs to traduce the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> of his <hi>Moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty,</hi> and to multiply <hi>Injuries</hi> upon his <hi>People.</hi> Which <hi>proceeding</hi> of theirs we cannot but look upon as ſomwhat <hi>irregular,</hi> conſidering their deep <hi>obligations</hi> to <hi>This Crown;</hi> together with their long <hi>Experience</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> which they have found upon ſeveral <hi>trials,</hi> and <hi>occaſions,</hi> to be either <hi>the moſt neceſſary Friend,</hi> or <hi>the moſt dangerous Enemy</hi> to their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the <hi>Earth.</hi> But whether they have done <hi>well,</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi> we are not to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48101:3"/>having only obtain'd leave, nakedly to publiſh the <hi>Fact</hi> of the <hi>Caſe,</hi> ſubmitting the <hi>merits</hi> of it to all <hi>Indifferent Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Better underſtanding of the whole Affair, we are to advertiſe the <hi>Reader,</hi> that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> out of a <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Generous diſpoſition</hi> to preſerve a <hi>fair Intelligence</hi> with the <hi>States</hi> above-mention'd, (and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding divers motives, and provocations to the contrary) hath been graciouſly pleaſed, ſince his happy <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> to renew an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance</hi> with them, and leave the <hi>Adjuſtment</hi> of, and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for the <hi>Damages</hi> done to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by thoſe of the ſaid <hi>Provinces,</hi> to a <hi>long,</hi> and <hi>deliberate</hi> way of <hi>deciſion;</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> obliterating many <hi>paſt miſdemeanors,</hi> in order to a better Correſpondence for the <hi>future;</hi> and promiſing to himſelf undoubtedly a <hi>Return</hi> anſwerable to ſo great a <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> Inſtead whereof, they have only rendred further <hi>diſ-Obligations,</hi> and <hi>Reproaches;</hi> ſupplying a palpable <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> with a proportional <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>Confidence,</hi> and <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi> Witneſs the <hi>diſhonourable Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> they have made of his <hi>Majeſties long-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance;</hi> together with the <hi>Peremptory Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> they have paſt upon the <hi>Engliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48101:3"/>and all This, without ſo much as a thought either of a <hi>Pertinent Reply,</hi> or a <hi>Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Satisfaction.</hi> Which we do the leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at; <hi>Firſt,</hi> in regard that the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> of our <hi>Pretences</hi> are effectually <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable;</hi> having ſuffered ſo ſtrict an <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> (even by the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf) and after <hi>That</hi> having been made out upon ſo <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>undeniable Proofs,</hi> that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to add any thing, either to the <hi>Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>Debate,</hi> or to the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> And in the <hi>next</hi> place, as to the point of <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> (not to aggravate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) we ſhall content our ſelves to ſay, That meaſuring things <hi>to come</hi> by things <hi>paſt,</hi> we did not find much reaſon to <hi>expect</hi> it; and ſo we ſhall leave them to the fate of their own Errors. But in the mean time, for the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſing</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and for the <hi>manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>our own Integrity,</hi> we ſhall preſent the <hi>Reader</hi> in this following publication, <hi>firſt,</hi> with A CATALOGUE <hi>of the</hi> DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAGES <hi>for which the</hi> ENGLISH <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> REPARATION, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>That,</hi> with our <hi>Neighbours Recrimination</hi> upon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> under the <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> of A LIST <hi>of the</hi> DAMAGES, ACTIONS,
<pb facs="tcp:48101:4"/>
               <hi>and</hi> PRETENCES <hi>whereof the</hi> EAST-INDIA-COMPANY <hi>of the</hi> LOW-COUNTRIES <hi>do promiſe Themſelves to have</hi> REPARATION <hi>and</hi> SATIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FACTION: With the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſubjoyn'd to the ſeveral and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Points of their <hi>Demands,</hi> remitting it upon the <hi>whole,</hi> to <hi>God, Angels,</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> to <hi>Judge betwixt</hi> Us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48101:4"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE OF THE DAMAGES For which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> demand <hi>Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> And, </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> Of the <hi>Damages</hi> which the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India-Company</hi> has ſuſtein'd by the <hi>Eaſt-Indian-Company</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COncerning the <hi>Ship</hi> call'd the <hi>May-flower,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whereof one <hi>William Curtis</hi> was the <hi>Commander:</hi> Who (being <hi>Agent</hi> alſo for the <hi>Engliſh-Company</hi>) having obtein'd liberty from the Queen of <hi>Acheene</hi> to traffique there, was about the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>Aug:</hi> 1658, <hi>old ſtyle,</hi> debarr'd of all Commerce, by one <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> who at that time commanded 3 <hi>Ships</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Eaſt-Indian-Company</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> and ſeiz'd <hi>Three Thouſand Eight Hundred Seventy and Eight pounds</hi> of <hi>Pepper</hi> which the ſaid Ship had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to lade with, forcing the ſaid <hi>Curtis</hi> to depart
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48101:5"/>Empty; and nothing of this was known at <hi>London</hi> upon the <hi>Tenth</hi> of <hi>January following,</hi> 165 8/9.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Ship</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> (one <hi>Nicholas Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diford, Commander</hi>) which came before <hi>Bantam</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1658, <hi>old ſtyle:</hi> which was forbidden, and hinder'd to <hi>Traffique</hi> there, by certain <hi>Netherland Ships</hi> then upon the Place, and by the <hi>General</hi> of <hi>Batavia,</hi> by whom the ſaid Ship was conſtrain'd to depart without her lading, and alſo neceſſitated to ſtay in the <hi>Indies</hi> till her <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> was ſpent, and forced at laſt to return in the <hi>Winter,</hi> and ſo ſhe was loſt. Of This likewiſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was known at <hi>London</hi> upon the <hi>Tenth</hi> of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary following,</hi> 165 8/9.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Ship</hi> the <hi>Advice;</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>(Robert Mayne, Commander)</hi> which being arrived at <hi>Bantam</hi> about the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>October</hi> 1658, <hi>Old Style,</hi> was in like manner as the <hi>Dragon</hi> forbidden all Commerce there, and forc'd to depart. And neither was this known at <hi>London</hi> upon the <hi>Tenth</hi> of <hi>January follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 165 8/9.</p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>Ship Marigold;</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>(John Connis, Commander)</hi> which arriving at <hi>Bantam</hi> about the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>February</hi> 1658, <hi>Old Style;</hi> one <hi>Keyſer,</hi> who commanded at that time 5 <hi>Ships</hi> before the Place, ſhot at the ſaid Ship, and hinder'd her either to Enter, or Traffique there, ſo that ſhe was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to go her way.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Factory</hi> of <hi>Jambee</hi> in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Summatra,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> upon the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1659, <hi>Old Style:</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48101:5"/>When <hi>Peter de Goyer, Principal</hi> of the <hi>Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> at <hi>Jambee,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan Clas</hi> his <hi>Second,</hi> with about 40 <hi>Dutch</hi>-Men, and 150 <hi>Slaves,</hi> all arm'd, and in form of an <hi>Enemy,</hi> enter'd by force into the <hi>Magazin</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in which outrage the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh were very much damnified.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship</hi> called the <hi>Merchants Delight,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>(Thomas Bell, Commander)</hi> arriving at <hi>Bantam</hi> in 1659. <hi>Old Style,</hi> was hindred from either Entring or Trading there, by certain Ships of the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> who were there at that time; and ſo ſhe was enforced to depart thence.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the <hi>Merchant of Conſtantinople, (Robert Brown, Commander)</hi> in the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>Sept:</hi> 1659. <hi>Old Style,</hi> ſailing betwixt <hi>Vingola</hi> and <hi>Goa,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>India,</hi> was attacqued by 7 <hi>Ships</hi> in the Service of the <hi>Dutch-Eaſt-India-Company,</hi> whereof <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Beeter</hi> was <hi>Vice-Admiral,</hi> who took by force out of the ſaid Ships, <hi>One Thouſand Nine Hundred Seventy and Eight Granades, Fifty Nine Iron Guns,</hi> and <hi>Three Braſs Morter-pieces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Monyes diſburs'd about 166 1/2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> to make a Proviſion of <hi>Ships, Victuals,</hi> and all other <hi>Neceſſaries</hi> for the <hi>poſſeſſing, planting,</hi> and <hi>fortifying</hi> of the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Pouleron.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48101:6"/>
               <head>Damages <hi>ſuſteined by the</hi> Dutch-Weſt-Indian Company.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Factory</hi> of <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> was upon the firſt of <hi>May</hi> 1659. <hi>Old Style,</hi> burnt, and ruin'd, together with all the <hi>Merchandize</hi> and <hi>Moveables</hi> therein, by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who were then in the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> and in the Service of the <hi>Dutch-Weſt-Indian-Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Factory</hi> of <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> after that the ſame was re-built, and well furniſhed with ſeveral ſorts of Merchandizes, for the Trade of that place, was burnt again upon the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1661. <hi>Old Style,</hi> with all the Merchandizes, and Moveables in the ſame, by ſome whom thoſe of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land-Eaſt-Indie Company</hi> had <hi>hyr'd</hi> for that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Damages <hi>ſuſteined by the</hi> Engliſh Turkey-Company.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Reformation,</hi> belonging to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>London,</hi> laden at <hi>Scanderon</hi> in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1659. as ſhe was quietly ſailing in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranean,</hi> was there ſeized, upon the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1660. by a certain Ship which came from <hi>Holland,</hi> call'd the <hi>Holy Mary,</hi> whereof <hi>Lawrence Andreas</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Free-Trade,</hi> deſign'd from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Scanderon,</hi> by ſome Merchants belonging to the ſaid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48101:6"/>Company, in the year 1659. was ſeiz'd upon the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1660, by the ſaid <hi>Holy Mary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Damages</hi> ſuſteined by other <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Ship,</hi> the <hi>Experience</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>(John Kingſman, Commander)</hi> was ſeiz'd upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> by one <hi>Quaerts,</hi> and others of <hi>Zealand,</hi> in the year 1660.</p>
               <p>Concerning a <hi>French Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> call'd <hi>the Golden Sun, (Nicolas de Breton du Pre, Commander) Edward Adams</hi> Merchant of <hi>London,</hi> as well for himſelf as for other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, demands to have ſatisfaction for the Merchandizes belonging to them, which were taken in the ſaid Ship, in the year 1660. upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal</hi> by <hi>four Zealand Men of War,</hi> commanded by <hi>Philip Ros, Touſain le Sage, Albert Johnſon,</hi> and the <hi>Maſters Mate</hi> of the Ship of <hi>Matthias Quaerts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Falcon, (Hendrick Hughes, Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> was ſeiz'd upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> upon the 31<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>May,</hi> 1660, by one <hi>Claus Rous,</hi> and another of <hi>Zealand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> Saint <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>(Emanuel Hart, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> who had taken aboard ſome <hi>Negros</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guinne,</hi> and <hi>barter'd</hi> them for <hi>Sugars</hi> and <hi>other Commodities</hi> at <hi>Baghia</hi> in <hi>Brazil</hi>) was ſeiz'd in his Return in <hi>June,</hi> 1661, by a <hi>Zealand Man of War,</hi> call'd <hi>the Golden Port of Middleburgh,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48101:7"/>whereof <hi>Cornelius Thrumcap</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the <hi>Merchants Delight,</hi> belonging to one <hi>John Young,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants, (John Bonner, Commander)</hi> having ſet ſail from <hi>Dover</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> was ſeized upon near to <hi>Cape Corſo</hi> in <hi>Guiney,</hi> about <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1661, by a Ship call'd the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Weſt-Indie Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Paragon,</hi> belonging to <hi>Bernard Sparke, John Cooke,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> (whereof one <hi>John Bariford</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi>) laden at <hi>Topſam.</hi> near to <hi>Exeter</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and bound for <hi>Guiney,</hi> was ſeiz'd about the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1661, by <hi>two Ships</hi> belonging to the <hi>Netherland Weſt-Indie-Company;</hi> the one, call'd the <hi>Amſterdammer</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> (whereof <hi>Aaron Couzens</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi>) and the <hi>other,</hi> call'd the <hi>Arms of Amſterdam,</hi> (whereof <hi>Nicholas Yole</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>)</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the <hi>Daniel,</hi> (belonging to <hi>John Knight, Thomas Knight, Henry Oakes,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> and commanded by the ſaid <hi>Henry Oakes</hi>) ſet ſail from <hi>London</hi> about <hi>May,</hi> 1661, to go for the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> and was ſeiz'd in a hoſtile manner by a Ship of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Netherland Weſt-Indie Company,</hi> call'd the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> whereof one <hi>Aaron Couzens</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the <hi>Brotherhood</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> (belonging to <hi>Peter Caulier, Bartholomew Caulier, Abraham Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> and <hi>John Beverley,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi>) was ſeized upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48101:7"/>
                  <hi>February,</hi> 1655, <hi>Old Style,</hi> by one <hi>Cox, Commander</hi> of the <hi>Fregat,</hi> call'd <hi>Gat;</hi> and one <hi>Yapoone, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> of a Ship call'd the <hi>Kater,</hi> both of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by the <hi>Netherland Weſt-Indie Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> call'd the <hi>Rappa Hanoeck,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> (belonging to one <hi>John Jeffryes,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi>) laden at <hi>London,</hi> and deſign'd for the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> was ſeiz'd near to <hi>Cape Lopes,</hi> about the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> 1656, by two <hi>Netherland Ships;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> call'd the <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> commanded by one <hi>John Serael</hi> of <hi>Munekedam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship, Sarah,</hi> belonging to one <hi>Ann Leuellin,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <hi>Adminiſtratrix</hi> of one <hi>Robert Leuellin,</hi> (Merchant) <hi>Humphry Beane,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> (whereof <hi>Arthur Perkins</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) was ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1656, near to <hi>Cape Lopes</hi> by <hi>two Ships</hi> of thoſe Countries; the one call'd the <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the <hi>other,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> commanded by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Serael</hi> of <hi>Munekedam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>Fortune</hi> (belonging to one <hi>Conſtant Silveſter,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi>) was ſeiz'd about <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1656; near to <hi>Cape Lopes,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> whereof the ſaid <hi>John Serael</hi> of <hi>Munekedam</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship, Blackboy</hi> of <hi>Dover;</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> (belonging to one <hi>Arnold Breames,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> whereof <hi>Ralph Wood</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) laden at <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48101:8"/>in <hi>January</hi> 1660, was ſeiz'd about the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 1661, near to <hi>Comenda,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> by a Ship of thoſe Countries, call'd <hi>The Grafenna;</hi> which came from the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Mina,</hi> and carried thither the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                  <hi>Speedwell</hi> (belonging to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>John Taylor,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Robert Cooke</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi>) purſuing her Voyage from <hi>Gottenburgh</hi> for <hi>London,</hi> was ſeiz'd in <hi>May</hi> 1657, by a <hi>Man of War</hi> of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> Commanded by <hi>Peter Tyſen,</hi> who carried the ſaid <hi>Ship</hi> to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and there ſold her, together with her entire lading, to one <hi>William Hunton, Merchant</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> without any <hi>legal proceeding</hi> or <hi>ſentence</hi> againſt her.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
                  <hi>Lubeck</hi> (whereof <hi>Ditmar Pieterſon</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi>) being laden in <hi>May,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Nisbet,</hi> and <hi>Richard Metcalfe</hi> of the City of <hi>York,</hi> with 1858 <hi>Tun</hi> of <hi>Rye,</hi> at <hi>Strale-Sond</hi> in <hi>Pomerland,</hi> to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported for <hi>Hull</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> was ſeiz'd upon by five <hi>Netherland men of War,</hi> viz. <hi>One</hi> commanded by <hi>Edward Anchuyſen, another</hi> by <hi>Laurence Deden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp</hi> of <hi>Groningen,</hi> a <hi>Third</hi> by one Captain <hi>Sunck, another</hi> call'd the <hi>black Eagle,</hi> and the <hi>Fifth</hi> the <hi>golden Lyon,</hi> which carried the ſaid Ship to <hi>Copenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> and there diſpoſed of her lading.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
                  <hi>Anne</hi> and <hi>Margaret,</hi> (belonging to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Weſcombe, Nicholas Warren,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Merchants</hi> of <hi>London</hi>) having taken in her Lading at <hi>Tunis,</hi> with ſome Merchandiſe, in the year 1658, for the ſervice of the ſaid Proprietors, was ſeized in her Voyage to <hi>Legorn,</hi> by a Ship of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48101:8"/>call'd the <hi>Geldre,</hi> whereof <hi>John Jacobſon Zens</hi> was <hi>Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> John (Cornelius Van Ringen, Maſter)</hi> belonging to one <hi>Vincent de la Barre,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> being bought by their order at <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1658, and there laden, on deſign to go for <hi>Calbarine</hi> to trade for <hi>Negroes,</hi> was taken near to the Port of <hi>Calbarine</hi> by a Ship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Netherland-Weſt-Indie Company,</hi> and confiſcated at <hi>Calbarine</hi> aforeſaid; notwithſtanding that the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> had given permiſſion to the ſaid <hi>Veſſel</hi> to the end aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> the <hi>Aſſada Merchant,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> being employed by Mr. <hi>Nicholas Buckeridge</hi> to go to <hi>Bantam</hi> to take in ſuch Goods as the ſaid <hi>Buckeridge</hi> had prepared there, in <hi>July</hi> 1657, was hindered by a Ship of the <hi>Netherland-Eaſt-Indie Company,</hi> which was ſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly from <hi>Batavia:</hi> And this was not known at <hi>London</hi> the 10/20 of <hi>January</hi> 165 8/9, as will be made to appear.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
                  <hi>Anne Piercy</hi> (belonging to <hi>Daniel Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax, John Dethick,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi>) as ſhe purſued her Voyage from <hi>England</hi> in <hi>March</hi> 1656, to go to <hi>Pantelorea,</hi> between <hi>Legorn,</hi> and <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and being deſign'd for <hi>Smyrna,</hi> was aſſaulted by a Ship of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> call'd the <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> whereof one <hi>Ree Morice</hi> (a <hi>Hollander</hi>) was <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander;</hi> who burnt, and ſunk her with all her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> the <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> belonging to <hi>John Allen,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48101:9"/>and <hi>Matthew Babb, Engliſh Merchants,</hi> (whereof <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Blake</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) being ſent to <hi>Bobuee</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> with deſign to trade for <hi>Negroes,</hi> was ſeiz'd in a hoſtile manner, in the <hi>month</hi> of <hi>January</hi> 1661, by a Ship belonging to the <hi>Weſt-Indie Company</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands,</hi> call'd the <hi>Poſt-horſe,</hi> which carried her to the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Mina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> the <hi>Lyon Providence</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Sir William Thompſon,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> who laded the ſaid Ship at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for <hi>Guiney</hi>) was ſeiz'd on in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1656, near to <hi>Cape Lopez</hi> in <hi>Guiney,</hi> by two Ships belonging to the <hi>Netherland-Weſt-Indie Company;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> call'd the <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and the <hi>other,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> whereof <hi>John Serael</hi> of <hi>Munekedam</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> call'd the <hi>Brazil-Fregat</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>John Buſhell, Edward Buſhell,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi>) was ſeiz'd between <hi>Angola</hi> and <hi>Fernambuck,</hi> in the year 1657, by a Ship of <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> call'd The <hi>Sluce,</hi> whereof one <hi>Quaerts</hi> was <hi>Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> 
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> (whereof <hi>Captain Sprag</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) was ſeized in the <hi>Road</hi> of <hi>St. Martins</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>July</hi> 1660, by <hi>Three men of War</hi> in the ſervice of the <hi>States General,</hi> and commanded by Captain <hi>Enno Dondeſtarre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> 
                  <hi>Content of London</hi> (whereof <hi>William Jordan</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) as ſhe ſet ſail from the <hi>Downes,</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1661, on deſign to trade upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48101:9"/>the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> was ſeized there by a Ship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Netherland-Weſt-Indie Company,</hi> call'd the <hi>Holy Barbara,</hi> which carried the ſaid <hi>Engliſh Ship</hi> to a certain <hi>Iſland</hi> call'd the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Gene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship, True love,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> belonging to Sir <hi>Draper,</hi> and other <hi>Engliſh Merchants (Edmund Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Commander)</hi> for certain Goods taken out of her belonging to <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and for the freight of ſuch Merchandizes as were taken out belonging to <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghueſes,</hi> near to <hi>St. Michell,</hi> (one of the <hi>Weſtern Iſlands</hi>) by <hi>Abraham Dominicus, Commander</hi> of the Ship, <hi>The Dauphine</hi> of <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> in 1659. As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for Merchandizes taken out of the ſame in her Voyage between <hi>Lisbon</hi> and <hi>New-England,</hi> in the year 1660, by the Ships, the <hi>St. John Baptiſt,</hi> whereof <hi>John Lopez</hi> was <hi>Commander,</hi> the <hi>Catharine,</hi> Captain <hi>Oncruiſe, Commander,</hi> and the <hi>golden Burgh,</hi> Captain <hi>Thrumcap, Commander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship, Charles,</hi> belonging to M<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>James Burkin,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> (whereof one <hi>John Blackler</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi>) being laden for their Particular, upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiney,</hi> was ſeiz'd upon the ſaid Coaſt, in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1661, by a Ship belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Netherland Weſt-Indie Company,</hi> call'd the <hi>Amſterdammer</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> (one <hi>Aaron Couzens, Commander</hi>) and carried by him to <hi>Caſtle Mina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> 
                  <hi>Packet Fregat</hi>) whereof <hi>Edward Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was <hi>Maſter,</hi> (belonging to one <hi>James Drawater,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi>) being laden at <hi>Genoa,</hi> and <hi>Final,</hi> and deſign'd for <hi>London,</hi> was ſeiz'd in her Voyage at the <hi>Streights Mouth,</hi> by a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48101:10"/>
                  <hi>Netherland Ship,</hi> call'd the <hi>Golden Duyk,</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Captain <hi>Albert Cock,</hi> about the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1654, <hi>Old Style,</hi> and carried to <hi>Cadiz</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship, with part of her lading was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored: And <hi>Satisfaction</hi> is now demanded for the reſt, and for the <hi>Cordage</hi> of the ſaid Ship.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> the <hi>Conſtant Mary,</hi> belonging to <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bellars, Thomas Fowke, Richard Glover,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> (whereof one <hi>Daniel Leſter</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi>) being laden at <hi>London,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for <hi>Guiney,</hi> was ſeized upon the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1654, <hi>Old Style,</hi> about 20 <hi>Leagues</hi> from the <hi>Cape Saint Vincent,</hi> by a <hi>Netherland man of War,</hi> call'd the <hi>Holy Cicilie,</hi> whereof one <hi>Hanſe Alburge</hi> was <hi>Commander,</hi> being, as he confeſſed, in the Service of the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> 
                  <hi>Noſtra Seigniora di Remedia,</hi> having taken Merchandizes abord in the Port of <hi>Macaſſar,</hi> upon the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Celebes,</hi> in the <hi>Great Indies,</hi> in the year 1660, <hi>Old Style,</hi> was ſeized the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> of the ſame year, by <hi>two Ships of War</hi> in the Service of the <hi>Netherland Eaſt-Indie Company,</hi> which carried the ſaid Ship to <hi>Batavia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> the <hi>Leopard,</hi> (belonging to <hi>Nicholas Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chart</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi>) was ſeized near to <hi>Capo Blanco,</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1656, by the <hi>Challoup</hi> of a <hi>Holland man of War,</hi> (both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Netherland Weſt-Indie Company</hi>) and carried to the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Arangeny,</hi> at <hi>Capo Blanco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> the <hi>Golden Sun</hi> of <hi>Lubeck,</hi> having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48101:10"/>her 110 <hi>Laſt</hi> of <hi>Rye,</hi> and being <hi>freighted</hi> at <hi>Revel,</hi> (upon the <hi>Baltick Sea</hi>) by one <hi>Thomas Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Merchant</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and for his accompt, in the year 1659, was ſeiz'd by ſome <hi>Netherland men of War,</hi> belonging to the <hi>States General,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Admiral Opdam,</hi> who ſent the ſaid Ship to the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> call'd the <hi>Dove</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one <hi>Jacob Granger, John Warner,</hi> and <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Merchants, (John Johnſon, Maſter)</hi> was ſeiz'd near to <hi>Shetland,</hi> on the <hi>North-ſide</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by a <hi>Netherland man of War,</hi> and ſent to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuyſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ship,</hi> call'd the <hi>Rebecca</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> 
                  <hi>(George Buckenham, Master)</hi> was ſeiz'd by a <hi>man of War</hi> of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> (commanded by one <hi>Derwelly</hi>) and carried into <hi>Zealand,</hi> and there they unladed a part of her Goods, before any Tryal in the <hi>Admiralty;</hi> and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Addreſſes and Applications which were made to the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>Zealand,</hi> the ſaid Ship of War was ſuffer'd to return to Sea and eſcape.</p>
               <p>Seized by <hi>Admiral Opdam,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> and other Veſſels un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Command, upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in the year <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> abord the Fleet, or <hi>Portugueſe Ships,</hi> a quantity of <hi>Sugars,</hi> and other Merchandizes belonging to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and carried away to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam, and other parts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48101:11"/>
            <head>A <hi>LIST</hi> of the <hi>Damages, Actions,</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes,</hi> whereof the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> do promiſe themſelves to have <hi>Reparation,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Damages</hi> which the <hi>Company</hi> hath <hi>really</hi> ſuffer'd, or that have been <hi>cauſed</hi> to them, by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Counſellors</hi> deputed in the <hi>Colledge</hi> of the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Dutch</hi> Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> do repreſent, that Captain <hi>Abraham Vanderhulſt,</hi> having in the year 1657 taken a <hi>Portuguez</hi> Ship la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with <hi>Sugars,</hi> was forc'd by ſtorm to Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and though the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could not pretend any right, nor cognizance, in juſtice to the Prize, and much leſs ought they to ſeize her <hi>de facto,</hi> without any form or colour of <hi>Proceſs;</hi> Nevertheleſs the <hi>Engliſh Commiſſioners</hi> of <hi>Prize-goods</hi> taken by their men of War, paſſing over all conſiderations of good Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Hoſpitality, took away the ſaid Prize from the ſaid Captain, and delivered her to the <hi>Portugal Embaſſadour</hi> then at <hi>London,</hi> who diſpoſed of her: and the <hi>deputed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors</hi> do pretend that they ought to be re-imburſed of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the ſaid <hi>Prize, cum omni causâ &amp; acceſſione.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48101:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Eaſt-India-Company <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>having ſeen the Liſt of</hi> Damages, Actions, <hi>and</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes, <hi>exhibited againſt them by the</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands Eaſt-India-Company, <hi>do find it to be,</hi> A deliberate Maſs of FRIVOLOUS, INSOLENT, <hi>and</hi> UNJUST Demands, built upon Concluſions made without the leave of any Premiſes of TRUTH, REASON, <hi>or</hi> LAW OF NATIONS; <hi>as we hope all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial, and rational men will judge, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the</hi> Articles themſelves, <hi>but when they ſhall ſee this ſubſequent</hi> Anſwer.</head>
               <p>TO the <hi>firſt Article,</hi> we anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Engliſh <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1.</note> That no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is entred in the <hi>Admiralty Court;</hi> if there had, the queſtion would have born a hard diſpute in <hi>Law;</hi> Whether a Ship being taken as <hi>Prize,</hi> ſhall be brought into the Harbor of a Prince in <hi>Amity,</hi> with both the <hi>Taker,</hi> and the <hi>Taken,</hi> or to which of them the ſaid Ship ſhall be delivered?</p>
               <p>He that did reſide at <hi>Jambee</hi> for the Company of theſe Countries, having bought there in the Month of <hi>May,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note> 1660. a quantity of 700 <hi>Picols,</hi> or 85000 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>Pepper,</hi> at four <hi>Royals and a half</hi> the <hi>Picol,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did take it <hi>violently,</hi> and ſeized on it by <hi>force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>ſecond</hi> we ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 2.</note> That we know not of any ſuch <hi>Violence</hi> offered to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> as the taking of any <hi>pepper</hi> from them: They name not the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> by whom it was that the pretended force was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48101:12"/>done; nor have we received any <hi>pepper</hi> from <hi>Jambee,</hi> or any other part of <hi>India,</hi> but what our <hi>Factors</hi> have paid for, and placed the money to our Accompt: Nor have we ever had any the leaſt hint of the matter of fact complained of in this <hi>Article;</hi> But we have very good proofs of ſuch things attempted againſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> in <hi>That Port,</hi> and elſewhere, by the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and had not the greater Juſtice of the Magiſtrates of the place relieved us, we had had much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of our Loſſes in that kind then we can have to hope that if they had been done, the <hi>Hollanders Company</hi> would have made us <hi>repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 3.</note> called Mr. <hi>Paul,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Ganara</hi> (a place not a League diſtant from <hi>Bilipatman,</hi> on the <hi>North-ſide</hi>) took by force, and carried away, a very great quantity of <hi>Rice,</hi> amounting to many <hi>hundred Laſts,</hi> which the <hi>Company</hi> of theſe Countries or their <hi>Agents</hi> had contracted for, and bought; (and this, notwithſtanding all the proteſtations of Mr. <hi>Keſtlerus,</hi> (who did then reſide there for the ſaid <hi>Company</hi>) againſt ſuch violence) which, was the cauſe that the Ship freighted by the <hi>Company,</hi> and deſign'd to go fetch the ſaid quantity of <hi>Rice,</hi> were not only retarded; but alſo that the <hi>Gathering</hi> in the mean time being paſt, not any of the ſaid Ships could accompliſh their Voyage; which cauſed a very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damage, and prejudice to the ſaid <hi>Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>Third Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 3.</note> we ſay, <hi>we know no ſuch man as Mr. Paul,</hi> nor ever heard any thing of <hi>Rice,</hi> bought for our Accompts at <hi>Canara,</hi> nor any wrong or injuries done them by our people there, and there being no time mention'd when it was done, the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> anſwers it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48101:12"/>
               <p>It is only by the Treaty,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 4.</note> made betwixt the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>This Eſtate,</hi> the 4/14 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1662. and not <hi>before,</hi> That it was agreed and Convened (amongſt other things) that <hi>Pouleron</hi> ſhould be reſtored to the ſaid King, or elſe to ſuch as ſhould by his Majeſty be fully Authorized in <hi>Writing</hi> under the <hi>Great Seal</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> And to that purpoſe the neceſſary Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhould be put into his Majeſties hands preſently after the <hi>Ratification</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Treaty,</hi> his Majeſty having alſo demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid Orders from their <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> by his Letters of the 18 of <hi>December</hi> of the ſame year, which were then accordingly expedited: And nevertheleſs, thoſe of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> of <hi>England</hi> made no difficulty to ſend their Ships and Men into the <hi>Indies</hi> about <hi>two moueths</hi> before, to take poſſeſſion thereof; who alſo accordingly did addreſs themſelves to the <hi>General,</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Batavia;</hi> and ſummon'd them to give them the neceſſary orders for the rendring to them the ſaid Iſland. And though the ſaid <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> had no Authority to do it, becauſe that difference had not as yet been ended in <hi>Europe;</hi> they were nevertheleſs ſo bold to go thither without any order or command from <hi>Batavia:</hi> ſo that the ſaid <hi>General,</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> foreſeeing the diſorders that might thereupon enſue, even to the ſhedding of Blood; particularly ſince they could not know with what intent the <hi>Engliſh</hi> went that way, were neceſſitated for fear of ill conſequence, as alſo for the conſervation of the Forts, Places, and Goods of the <hi>Company,</hi> to ſend thither with all ſpeed a recruit of Ships and Men, by which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were kept back, and hindred from undertaking any thing by violence, whereof they would have made uſe, but for that ſtop.</p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>Company</hi> doth demand <hi>re-imburſement</hi> of the Charges laid out and imployed to that purpoſe, comprehending therein the freight of the Ships, as alſo the Souldiers pay, and Mariners wages; and of the Victuals, and withall, a reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Affront made to the whole Nation, and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of their Reputation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They demand the Charges laid out by the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and the <hi>Damages</hi> by them ſuffered, whereof they pretend re-imburſement from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as alſo of the Damages ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been cauſed by them.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48101:13"/>
               <p>To the <hi>fourth</hi> we ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 4.</note> That for the firſt Affirmation on which they ground their whole diſcourſe, they cannot but know to the contrary in <hi>Fact;</hi> for they lay down that the Reſtitution of the <hi>Iſland Pouleron</hi> was not agreed on, but by the Treaty made between the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> the 4th / 14 of <hi>September</hi> 1662; Whereas they could not but remember, that by the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Treaty</hi> in 1662, they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to do it, <hi>in haec verba:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe of the</hi> Netherlands <hi>do faithfully promiſe, that if ſo be they are in poſſeſſion of the</hi> Iſlands, <hi>and</hi> Forts <hi>of</hi> Pouleron, <hi>or if they have been taken directly or indirectly by Them, or by their</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, <hi>or by any others in their Name, to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, give over, and forſake them; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them unto thoſe of the</hi> Engliſh Company, <hi>in the ſame ſtate and condition they enjoyed them during the time of the</hi> Treaty.</p>
               <p>And when notwithſtanding this <hi>Covenant</hi> they had deteined it, unto the year 1654; It was then agreed <hi>de Novo,</hi> by the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of <hi>Both Sides,</hi> and ratified by the <hi>States, in haec verba:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et praeterea Statuimus, ac Ordinamus, ut praedicta</hi> Societas Belgica <hi>cedat ac reſtituat</hi> Societati An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicae <hi>praedictae,</hi> Inſulam Pouleron <hi>eo in ſtatu &amp; conditione, in qua nunc eſt; ita tamen ut licitum ſit dictae</hi> Societati Belgicae <hi>tollere &amp; amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere ex inſulâ praedictâ</hi> apparatum Bellicum, Merces, Suppellectilem, <hi>&amp;</hi> omnia mobilia, <hi>ſi quae fortaſſis in dicta inſula habeant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that then the word of <hi>Reſtitution</hi> us'd in both thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> evinceth our original right to it; and convinceth them of their Injuſtice in diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48101:13"/>us, and deteining it ſo long from us: And neither of thoſe Articles obliges us to any Formalities of the <hi>King's Commiſſion,</hi> or more then a bare <hi>Demand</hi> of it, when we had a mind to receive it. And our Ships that were ſent to poſſeſs it being departed, as they confeſs, before the concluſion of the <hi>Treaty</hi> in 1662; and <hi>That Treaty</hi> containing nothing that derogates from the two former Treaties, they cannot but with monſtrous confidence accuſe us of proceeding irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly; eſpecially, when it ſhall be conſidered that our Ships carried not onely the <hi>King's Commiſſion</hi> under the <hi>Great Seal</hi> to poſſeſs and plant it, but even <hi>Orders</hi> alſo from <hi>their States</hi> and <hi>Company;</hi> Dated the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1660. The receipt of which, the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Batavia</hi> acknowledged by their Letter of the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>November</hi> 1661, and though in the ſame Letter, they ſay, that ſince the Date of thoſe Orders, they had by their laſt Ship out of <hi>Holland</hi> received Intelligence that <hi>new debates</hi> were ariſen between the <hi>two Companies,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we could not with Reaſon demand ſurrender of the ſaid <hi>Iſland,</hi> until they had farther Intelligence from their <hi>Maſters</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> yet our Commanders had both the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>their Maſters,</hi> and a <hi>juſt title</hi> to the liberty of ſailing into thoſe Seas to Trade, without the <hi>Hollanders</hi> leave or diſturbance. Nor was there any colour of <hi>Jealouſie</hi> given to the <hi>Dutch</hi> of any hoſtile deſign, when the <hi>Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> declared their Reſolution to follow their Maſters Orders, and went onely with two Merchants Ships provided for Trade, and planting the Iſland (if it had been amicably delivered as it ought to have been) and therefore we think it had been ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and imprudent for the Commanders of our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48101:14"/>Ships to have deſiſted from the proſecution of their Voyage, and demanding the Iſland upon the place, as it is in them now to demand of us ſatisfaction, for the expence of thoſe forces which they ſay they ſent to affront his Majeſtie, and keep us from our right; while under the Fictitious Pretenſe of a Jealouſie, they deſigned (according to their uſual practiſe) to give us a forcible and real interuption in our juſt courſe and liberty of Trade: for which, we hope in time to receive <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> againſt the like in future.</p>
               <p>After that the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> of theſe Countries had in the year 1655.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 5. Vide <hi>page</hi> 22. <hi>for the Anſwer.</hi>
                  </note> really paid in <hi>England,</hi> under good and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Acquittance, the Moneys contained in the <hi>Arbitrary ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> pronounced in the year 1654. by the Commiſſioners na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on both ſides, amounting unto the ſum of 88615 <hi>l. Sterling,</hi> by which they thought to have fully ſtopped all pretenſes, and therefore might ſafely order their Ships to take (in their return) the uſual <hi>Channel,</hi> and to thoſe that they diſpatch'd from hence, to land in <hi>England,</hi> as if they ſhould be thereunto forc'd by ſtorms or contrary winds, there to expect fair weather and a favourable wind: Nevertheleſs, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did not omit to raiſe new actions and pretenſes againſt this Company, as ſoon as they heard in the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1657, that there was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived in the ſaid <hi>Channel</hi> a Ship of the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> call'd <hi>Henrietta Louiſia;</hi> and they obtained preſently, by direction of their <hi>Admiralty,</hi> a <hi>Warrant</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to make a <hi>Seizure</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Ship,</hi> and of its <hi>Cargo,</hi> to the prejudice and contempt of the <hi>Treaty</hi> ſo lately made with them; and That, under a <hi>frivolous pretenſe</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh-Eaſt-India-Company,</hi> for the ſum of 100000 <hi>l. Sterling:</hi> and of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> Eſtabliſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diſaſter of <hi>Will. Courteen</hi> after his <hi>Bankrupt</hi> of the like ſum of 100000 <hi>l.</hi> But the ſaid Ship having very happily eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped their hands, the <hi>Admiralty</hi> did anew grant (in the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>November</hi> following) a <hi>ſecond</hi> leave for <hi>ſeizure,</hi> which was effectually executed upon the <hi>Ship</hi> call'd <hi>Sterling,</hi> which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48101:14"/>being departed from hence to go to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> was forc'd by ſtorm, to Harbor at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Company</hi> of this Country ſeeing the irregular and unjuſt proceedings of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to prevent ſuch like inconveniences for the future; hath been obliged to order their Ships (inſtead of paſſing the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi>) in their return, to go about by <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to take their way <hi>Northward,</hi> as they did formerly, which does not only cauſe that the Merchandizes arrive, and are ſold later every year then before, to the great damage and prejudice of the <hi>Company,</hi> which is thereby obliged to pay <hi>greater Wages;</hi> and their men are expos'd to greater and longer dangers, and ſuffer greater damages and inconveniencies, but they are alſo oblig'd, as well for the ſafety and preſervation of their Fleet when it is coming home, as for the refreſhing of the men, who coming from that Country hot, do ſuffer by the cold in making ſo long turns by the <hi>North,</hi> to fit every year a great number of <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Pinnaces</hi> to ſend before to meet them by the <hi>North.</hi> The <hi>Charges</hi> disburſed, and that muſt yet be disburſed to that purpoſe, and the <hi>Damages</hi> amounting to a moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſum, as it ſhall appear by the Accompt that ſhall be thereof given.</p>
               <p>From the time that the Company of theſe Countries did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the grant of ſeizing the ſaid Ship,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 6. Vide <hi>page</hi> 22. <hi>for the Anſwer.</hi>
                  </note> call'd <hi>Henrietta Louiſia</hi> was given, becauſe that about That time they did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the <hi>two Ships</hi> call'd <hi>Arnhem</hi> and the <hi>Caſtle of Honigen,</hi> which were to return by the <hi>Channel,</hi> they found themſelves obliged by a warrantable apprehenſion, and neceſſary care to cauſe ſome <hi>Men of War</hi> and <hi>Pinnaces</hi> to be made ready, and to depart with ſpeed, to meet and convoy the others; So that the <hi>re-imburſement</hi> of thoſe charges may juſtly be demanded from the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 7.</note> Whereas the <hi>Company</hi> aboveſaid apprehended ſome like ſeizures in all the Ports of <hi>England,</hi> they have been obliged expreſly to forbid the Ships they diſpatch from hence to enter there or caſt Anchor in the <hi>Road:</hi> which is the cauſe that many of their Ships finding themſelves often ſurprized by ſtorms, have been forc'd to come back and enter into the Ports of theſe Countries, to ſtay for a more favourable wind, to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48101:15"/>great prejudice of their Voyage, and expoſing themſelves to great danger; the damages thereby ſuffered, and by thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, amounting to a ſum alſo very conſiderable.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>fifth, ſixth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 5, 6, 7.</note> and <hi>ſeventh Articles,</hi> we think it ſufficient for <hi>Anſwer,</hi> that if their being conſcious to Themſelves of the injuries done by <hi>Them</hi> to the Subjects of <hi>This Kingdom,</hi> and yet not honeſt enough to be willing to make legal ſatisfaction, does fright them from paſſing with their Ships through the <hi>Channel,</hi> leſt they might fall within the <hi>Virge</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> they may Themſelves blame their own unreaſonable fears; but yet to ſhew the world how unreaſonably they would ground a pretenſe of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> for their <hi>own unjuſt Jealouſies;</hi> We deſire it may be noted, that all that they complain of, was <hi>an attempt of a Legal Proceeding againſt the two Ships,</hi> the <hi>Henrietta Louiſia,</hi> and <hi>L' Eſtourneau,</hi> one of which was never Touched with an Arreſt, and the other releaſed as ſoon as it was requeſted.</p>
               <p>During the War that thoſe of <hi>Bantam</hi> have begun againſt the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 8.</note> againſt all equity and reaſon; with ſo much perfidiouſneſs, that even the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been obliged to avouch, and teſtifie as much by their Letters: the ſaid <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> had no other means to oppoſe themſelves to it, and to do them hurt, then by keeping their <hi>Harbour</hi> and <hi>City ſurrounded,</hi> and <hi>beſieged</hi> with a <hi>Fleet</hi> of <hi>Men of War,</hi> and to hinder their <hi>Trade;</hi> and that there ſhould not go in or out the <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes</hi> and <hi>Proviſions</hi> they might have need of, thereby to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb them; ſo that they might be conſtrain'd to ſubmit to reaſon, or elſe to weaken them ſo much, that cauſing their Forces to draw neer, and aſſaulting them vigorouſly on the <hi>Land-ſide</hi> they might be utterly vanquiſhed thereby, and wholly ſubjected: The <hi>Experience</hi> and <hi>Event</hi> having alſo made it known, that they have been ſo much humbled thereby, that they have been forc'd to come to deſire peace, (as with joyned
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48101:15"/>hands) But the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who (by virtue of the <hi>Treaty</hi> made with them by this <hi>State</hi>) were obliged to be helpers to the <hi>Company</hi> of theſe Countries in this Encounter, ſo much the more, that it was They that were ſet upon; and that only by an averſion, and irrreconcileable hatred whereof the <hi>Moors</hi> are prepoſſeſſed againſt all <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> in lieu of helping them, have loſt no opportunity to oppoſe themſelves to our deſigns, and have endeavoured with their <hi>Ships</hi> to procure the <hi>Harbour</hi> free, and to make them loſe the Benefit of a <hi>ſiege</hi> which had coſt them ſo much trouble and charges; and in Conſequence, to cauſe the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> to be conſumed by thoſe means, becauſe That hath been the cauſe, that not only the ſaid <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Siege</hi> have endured far longer then they ſhould otherwiſe have done (which hath cauſed great prejudice to the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> and hath much vexed it) but alſo that they have been obliged to hinder the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to obtain their end, to have the ſaid <hi>Road ſurrounded</hi> and <hi>beſieged</hi> by a greater number of Ships, and thoſe bigger then otherwiſe they ſhould have needed to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy: ſo that beſides the other delays, hinderances, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, cauſed to the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> for that cauſe, in other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions they have been obliged to be at a very great charge, and have been very much incommodated with other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>eighth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 8.</note> We ſay it ought not to come in conſideration at all; becauſe no time is aſſigned of the fact, nor any perſon or Ships named; nor have we knowledge of any thing but our ſufferings, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time that ſome of their Ships lay before <hi>Bantam,</hi> unleſs they will call it a crime that we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured amicably to obtain from them the juſt liberty of Trade which the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> allows, and they denyed us: And <hi>we can gueſs at no other ground of that War, unleſs it were to force the King of</hi> Bantam <hi>to a</hi> Contract <hi>to</hi> exclude <hi>us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48101:16"/>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> know that the aboveſaid <hi>Company</hi> have ever treated with the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Acheen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 9.</note> as well for the <hi>Tynn</hi> which is bought at <hi>Perager,</hi> as principally for the <hi>Pepper</hi> which grows in the <hi>Weſtern Coaſt</hi> of the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Sumatra;</hi> by which <hi>Treaty,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Pepper</hi> is to be all delivered at a certain Rate, whereof there is an agreement made with the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of any other <hi>Nations,</hi> as the <hi>Company</hi> is likewiſe obliged on their ſide to go fetch all the <hi>Pepper</hi> at the ſaid rate. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have heretofore made ſuch <hi>Contracts,</hi> as well <hi>joyntly</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> as by <hi>themſelves</hi> with ſeveral of the <hi>Indians:</hi> for it doth appear by the <hi>Agreement</hi> made in the year 1619 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>two Eaſt-India Companies</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and that of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> for the <hi>re-eſtabliſhing</hi> of the Affairs of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> by the <hi>Approbation</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and of the <hi>States,</hi> That there had been then ſuch a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> made with the King of <hi>Acheen,</hi> by the which it was alſo agreed, how, and in what manner both the <hi>Companies</hi> could joyntly make ſuch a <hi>Contract</hi> with the King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> for the <hi>Pepper</hi> which groweth in his Country; and the ſame to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and formal excluſion of all other Nations, as well <hi>Indians,</hi> as <hi>Europeans,</hi> who would trade therewith. The which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly perform'd, and practiſed; And although for That rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were obliged not to trouble the <hi>Company</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in performance of the <hi>Agreements</hi> made (which do as yet remain in force) they have however always endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to fruſtrate the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> of the Benefit of the ſaid <hi>Contract,</hi> by indirect ways, and evil means, in corrupting the Inhabitants of that Country, in obliging them to ſell them the <hi>Tynn,</hi> and the <hi>Pepper,</hi> by the greater Price, or Rate, which they cauſed to be offered them from time to time, without taking any notice of the <hi>proteſts</hi> made by the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> or their <hi>Agents,</hi> againſt ſuch proceedings: ſo far that the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> not able to forbear any longer, was forced, for the obſervation and execution of the ſaid <hi>Contracts,</hi> to take up <hi>Arms</hi> to bring thoſe men to their <hi>Duties</hi> by meer <hi>ſtrength,</hi> they having been taken off, by the ill practices and cunning ways of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The peace was not ſo ſoon renewed with the ſaid <hi>Queen</hi> (as alſo the <hi>old Contracts</hi>) but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came in with their Ships with a deſign to diſappoint alſo the aboveſaid <hi>Company</hi> of that <hi>Pepper,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48101:16"/>if they could have done it; ſo that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been the movers, and given occaſion not only for the ſaid <hi>War</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> was forc'd to make againſt the Kingdom of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheen,</hi> with ſo exceſſive charges, but alſo by the ſleights they have made of their <hi>proteſts,</hi> they have obliged the <hi>Company</hi> to keep there continually a number of Ships to hinder the <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> to ſell their <hi>Tynn</hi> and <hi>Pepper</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by hidden and indirect ways, and fruſtrate thereby the <hi>Company</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> which hath cauſed a very conſiderable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and damage to the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> which doth conceive it ſelf to have a right of demanding reparation thereof from the <hi>Engliſh Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>third</hi> place, the Injuries, Affronts, and Hinderances, as alſo the troubles, and incumbrances, which the <hi>Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> hath procured to <hi>This Company,</hi> whereof <hi>This Company</hi> doth demand reparation, and refaction.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>ninth Article;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 9.</note> We know that they have made <hi>Contracts</hi> with the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Acheen</hi> both for <hi>Tynn</hi> and <hi>Pepper;</hi> and it may be <hi>excluſive</hi> to <hi>us;</hi> but if ſo, they have violated the expreſs terms of that <hi>Treaty</hi> 1619, which they miſreport for the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,</hi> in expreſs terms provides, as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That neither of the</hi> two Companies <hi>ſhall</hi> prevent, <hi>or</hi> exclude <hi>the other, for time to come, whether it be by means of</hi> Fortifications, <hi>or</hi> Contracts, <hi>that one would make hereafter in any part of the</hi> Indies: <hi>But</hi> all the Trade ſhall be free and common to one, and the other, in every place <hi>thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We do not deny, but where there is no obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the contrary, it may be lawful for them or us
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48101:17"/>to contract with any Prince or people, for the whole of any commodity of their growth or manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture; but if the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſay truth in their own <hi>allegations,</hi> that <hi>they have always had ſuch a</hi> Contract <hi>with the</hi> Queen <hi>of</hi> Acheen; they confeſs that they have injured us in it, contrary to the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Treaty</hi> 1619 aforeſaid. But ſuppoſing them now abſolved from that <hi>Article,</hi> and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that good neighbourhood which they ought to ſhew us, they have made ſuch uſe of that liberty as to contract with the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Acheen,</hi> and others, by the influence of their <hi>arms</hi> to exclude us from the Trade of their Countries; yet we being no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor conſenting to that <hi>Contract,</hi> cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be under any obligation, not to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſhare in the Trade, if either party be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to admit us; and if they do it to the violation of their <hi>Contract,</hi> the <hi>Contractant</hi> only is the perſon upon whom both by <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> the party inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red muſt have recourſe for ſatisfaction, and not upon us: And That eſpecially ſince thoſe <hi>Contracts</hi> have been for the moſt part extorted from the <hi>Natives</hi> by pure force of <hi>Arms,</hi> even while we have had our <hi>Factories</hi> amongſt them; and ſo have been <hi>fellow-ſufferers</hi> with the <hi>Natives</hi> in the injuries they have done by the War. And therefore <hi>We think it will be judged very frivolous in the</hi> Hollanders <hi>to require from</hi> us <hi>ſatisfaction for the expence</hi> of Their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Forces, <hi>by which they maintain the advantages of their firſt extorted</hi> Contract <hi>from the</hi> Natives <hi>to</hi> our prejudice.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48101:17"/>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have of late begun to introduce and practiſe in the <hi>Indies</hi> to protect and defend the <hi>Ships</hi> and <hi>Barques</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome <hi>Nations</hi> with whom <hi>This Company</hi> is in <hi>Wars</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them a <hi>Warrant,</hi> or <hi>Poſs-port,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 10.</note> whereby they do maintain that thoſe people ought to be free of any trouble, or moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And whereas that hath cauſed already many diſorders, and diſtaſtes which apparently will breed open hoſtilities, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid <hi>Company</hi> doth beſeech the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> to give ſuch neceſſary orders that ſuch things may ceaſe, for want of which they do proteſt that they cannot be blamed of the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences which may thereby happen.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>tenth Article;</hi> we ſay; It is true,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 10.</note> that we have and do practiſe to give <hi>Paſs-ports</hi> to the <hi>Ships</hi> of thoſe <hi>Natives</hi> that are in friendly <hi>commerce</hi> with us: by which; all the Commanders of Ships in our ſervice, are required not to hinder or diſturb them; but rather to lend them aſſiſtance: and the <hi>Holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> do the like; and we know not why it may not be as free for <hi>us as them:</hi> And if we have given ſuch <hi>Paſs-ports</hi> to <hi>Our friends</hi> whom the <hi>Hollanders</hi> may pleaſe to call <hi>Their Enemies,</hi> and therefore attaque them, We know not of any diſorders that have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed upon it; but it ſeems by the <hi>confidence</hi> of the <hi>requeſt</hi> of this <hi>Article</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the <hi>threat</hi> of an <hi>open War,</hi> and <hi>Proteſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him, in caſe of his <hi>non-complyance,</hi> that the <hi>Netherlands Company</hi> doth moſt <hi>inſolently</hi> pretend in their <hi>own names,</hi> to be <hi>ſole Sovereigns</hi> of thoſe Seas, and would have his Majeſty own them for ſuch, but that being a matter of <hi>State,</hi> this Company leaves it to his <hi>Majeſties Royal Reſentment.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48101:18"/>
               <p>And whereas it is daily more and more ſeen that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have no other intent but to trouble and moleſt <hi>This Company</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 11.</note> and to offer any kind of injuries, and affronts to their men; and That only to pick a quarrel, that they may have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe to make ſome <hi>proteſts;</hi> ſince they have not ſtuck openly to <hi>declare,</hi> that they get a greater benefit from thoſe <hi>proteſts,</hi> then by their <hi>Trade;</hi> ſeeking only thereby to alter the peace and quietneſs between both Nations. The which doth clearly appear by the <hi>Impertinent pretenſes</hi> which they have thought good to produce here, and to make uſe thereof, the which doth much concern the <hi>Authorities</hi> of <hi>both Eſtates</hi> to hinder as ſoon as poſſible, and to oppoſe vigorouſly: And the <hi>Companies</hi> of <hi>theſe Countries</hi> do demand that it may be provided thereto, and remedied as ſoon as can be: Above all, that they may be inſtructed how to govern and carry themſelves in the <hi>Indies,</hi> in regard of that Nation; becauſe that having ſurrounded or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged any <hi>Enemies</hi> place, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhall endeavour to get in, or land with their Ships, and ſo <hi>vice verſa,</hi> becauſe that hath cauſed many diſtaſtes and diſorders ſome years ſince paſt.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>eleventh Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 11.</note> we can but ſay that the <hi>whole affirmation</hi> of it is <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> and <hi>falſe,</hi> and will never be believed unleſs they can perſwade the world to judge that our <hi>peaceable endeavours</hi> to follow any part of the <hi>right</hi> of our <hi>Trade</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> is a <hi>declared intention</hi> to <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>diſquiet</hi> the <hi>Netherlands Company,</hi> and to <hi>injure</hi> and <hi>affront Their people:</hi> Nor can it poſſibly be credited, that we ſhould attempt <hi>to injure or affront them upon deſign to quarrel there, that we might have a pretenſe for</hi> Proteſts, <hi>and boaſt that we had gotten more by That then by our Trade;</hi> For <hi>firſt;</hi> We have not for many years laſt paſt been in a condition in <hi>thoſe Seas</hi> to conteſt our <hi>right</hi> with them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48101:18"/>could not be ſo inconſiderate, as to provoke thoſe whoſe <hi>avarice</hi> and <hi>might,</hi> would, could and hath deſtroyed our intereſts. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It were as <hi>ridiculous</hi> for any man to <hi>believe,</hi> as it is <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> in them to <hi>affirm,</hi> that we ſhould get by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts</hi> againſt <hi>Them,</hi> when hitherto it is notorious to the whole world, that we never obtained from them after the cleareſt conviction of them, <hi>Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of one <hi>tenth part</hi> of thoſe <hi>loſſes</hi> which have been brought upon us, by <hi>Their Robbery,</hi> and <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> But we can with very great truth affirm, that when their people have taken our Ships and Goods, and could not deny but the Act was unjuſt, that they replied; <hi>It was better for their</hi> Maſters <hi>to pay for it at home, when we could get it, then for them not to improve all ways and means to diſcourage us in the Trade.</hi> And whereas in the <hi>Cloſe</hi> of this <hi>Article,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands Company</hi> preſume to prejudge the differences now depending, and to inſtruct both <hi>Our</hi> and <hi>Their Sovereignty,</hi> in what they aſſume to judge to be their <hi>duty.</hi> We ſhall onely ſay, that when his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall in his <hi>Royal Wiſdom</hi> think fit to eſtabliſh any <hi>regulation</hi> between us, we ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully and cheerfully conform to it.</p>
               <p>Amongſt others, an <hi>Engliſh Ship,</hi> called the <hi>Surat Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 12.</note> being in <hi>May</hi> 1662, on the <hi>Road</hi> of <hi>Gameron,</hi> did force a <hi>Mooriſh Ship</hi> of <hi>Matulipatuan,</hi> which did carry <hi>two Flags</hi> of <hi>This Eſtate,</hi> to ſtrike down, and to take them off, in the view of all the World, which was no ſmall affront to the whole Nation.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48101:19"/>
               <p>To the <hi>twelfth Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 12.</note> we ſay; We know nothing of it; but were it ſo, <hi>That Company</hi> could not have had the <hi>Impudence</hi> to have made it an <hi>Objection,</hi> that an <hi>Engliſh Ship</hi> riding with the <hi>Engliſh Flag</hi> would not ſuffer the <hi>States Colours</hi> upon a <hi>Moors Ship</hi> to be <hi>born up</hi> in her <hi>preſence,</hi> unleſs they concluded themſelves, both <hi>Sovereigns</hi> of the <hi>Indian,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Seas,</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> at <hi>Home.</hi> But perchance they fancy, that this their frivolous and unknown complaint, might ſerve to ballance that <hi>unſufferable affront</hi> that was offer'd in <hi>February</hi> 16 62/63, to the <hi>Engliſh Flag</hi> of Saint <hi>George</hi> at <hi>Swallow Marine,</hi> in <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation;</hi> when <hi>Captain Bence,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Holland Ship, (Gouldſtloome)</hi> Riding <hi>Admiral</hi> there, firſt made faſte the ſaid <hi>Engliſh Flag</hi> to the <hi>Star-bord liſt</hi> of the <hi>main-top-ſail yard,</hi> where it hung <hi>half an hour;</hi> and was thence remov'd to the head of the <hi>main Maſt;</hi> and thence down to the <hi>Top,</hi> and there remained all day, <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Dutch Flag.</hi> And the ſame day, the <hi>Dutch</hi> landed, and marched with their <hi>Flags flying round</hi> the <hi>Engliſh yard,</hi> in <hi>deriſion</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Flag</hi> there <hi>on ſhore;</hi> and that they did the like with higher <hi>Inſolence</hi> about the <hi>Engliſh Houſe</hi> in the City of <hi>Surat</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Forces of <hi>This Company</hi> did beſiege lately the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cochin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 13.</note> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> which were in the Port of the ſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo far forgot themſelves, as to ſerve the Artillery of the ſaid City againſt the <hi>Beſiegers,</hi> and this directly againſt the <hi>Treaty</hi> made here with them in the <hi>Hague,</hi> the 6th of <hi>February,</hi> 1659. which ſaith expreſly, that <hi>both the</hi> Companies <hi>ſhall live quietly, and in good Intelligence together, and ſhall reciprocally
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48101:19"/>ſhew one another proofes of friendſhip, as well in the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>as</hi> elſewhere: for which, the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> doth demand reparation, and ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>thirteenth Article,</hi> we ſay;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 13.</note> We know not that any of our men ſerved as <hi>Gunners</hi> in the Town of <hi>Cochin</hi> againſt the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> or if they did, it is like it was done in defence of <hi>This Companies Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt There,</hi> which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had equally deſigned for <hi>deſtruction</hi> with that of thoſe whom they call their <hi>Enemies;</hi> and when our <hi>differences</hi> come to the <hi>teſt,</hi> it will then appear, <hi>which</hi> of the <hi>two Companies</hi> hath <hi>obſerved,</hi> or <hi>violated</hi> the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Amity</hi> made <hi>in Anno</hi> 1659.</p>
               <p>Whilſt in the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>April,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 14.</note> 1662. ſome <hi>Sea-men</hi> of this Country were about diverting themſelves neer the <hi>Road</hi> of <hi>Suali,</hi> in a Village call'd <hi>Selein Dammetyens,</hi> they were not only ill-uſed with Cudgels by ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> which hapned to come in, but alſo three of them were ſo much wounded, that one, call'd <hi>Paul Francis Schoone, fellow</hi> or <hi>Adjutant helper</hi> to the <hi>Gunner</hi> in the <hi>Ship</hi> called <hi>Buyenskereke,</hi> dyed of his wounds <hi>two days</hi> after, without any puniſhment inflicted on the <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh Preſident</hi> of <hi>Surat,</hi> called <hi>Matthew An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> although he was ſummoned and motion'd to do it: Therefore <hi>This Company</hi> cannot chuſe but demand reparation of the affront and wrong done to the whole Nation, and is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to maintain that there is an obligation to puniſh the guilty exemplarily.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>fourteenth,</hi> we ſay;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 14.</note> We conceive that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>This</hi> nor the <hi>tenth, eleventh, twelfth,</hi> and <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Articles,</hi> (being matters of <hi>State,</hi> and not of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48101:20"/>
                  <hi>Trade</hi>) do fall within the <hi>Cognizance</hi> of the <hi>fifteenth Article</hi> of the <hi>Laſt Treaty,</hi> and therefore ought not to be here admitted: But yet we <hi>Anſwer,</hi> that we know nothing of <hi>Paul Franc Schoone,</hi> his being <hi>baſtonaded</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to <hi>death;</hi> onely we find by good and ſufficient <hi>Atteſtation,</hi> dated at <hi>Sualy</hi> in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April</hi> 16 62/63; that about that time <hi>three Dutch-men</hi> aſſaulted <hi>two Engliſh-men</hi> in the open field, and one of the <hi>Dutch</hi> with his drawn knife ſtruck at the <hi>face</hi> of one <hi>Wilks,</hi> who receiv'd the <hi>ſtab</hi> on his <hi>hand;</hi> and when the <hi>Dutch-man</hi> was making a <hi>ſecond ſtab</hi> at the <hi>other Engliſh-man,</hi> one <hi>Brewer,</hi> (whom he wounded in the <hi>Arm</hi>) <hi>Brewer,</hi> in his own defence, ſtroke the <hi>Dutch-man</hi> with his <hi>ſtaff</hi> over the <hi>face,</hi> and felled him to the ground; and if the <hi>Dutch-man dyed</hi> of the <hi>blow,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> cannot be accuſed of a <hi>murther;</hi> when what he did, was <hi>ſe defendendo.</hi> But on the <hi>other ſide,</hi> we found that in <hi>April</hi> 1661, <hi>Joſeph Goodſon,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> and <hi>other Engliſh-men,</hi> were barbarouſly <hi>aſſaulted</hi> at <hi>Sualy,</hi> by the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon</hi> of the <hi>Dutch Ship, Henrietta Louiſia,</hi> and one <hi>John Abramſon,</hi> with drawn ſwords, and run into the belly the ſaid <hi>Chyrurgeon,</hi> and in few hours after dyed of his wounds. And another <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> one <hi>John Jones,</hi> endeavouring to reſcue the ſaid <hi>Joſ: Goodſon,</hi> was then likewiſe ſlain by the <hi>two Dutch</hi> parties.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48101:20"/>
               <p>That upon the 16. of <hi>March,</hi> 1662, about 30.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Hollanders</hi> entered into the <hi>Engliſh Bazar,</hi> with <hi>Lances, Swords, Clubs,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Colours flying,</hi> and enquired for <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> ſwearing by their <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and threatning the Death of all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> they could meet; but finding none, they brake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mans houſe adjacent, where they found an old man, a <hi>Servant</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Company,</hi> to whom they gave <hi>four Mortal wounds,</hi> and left him: And now <hi>let the whole world judge, whether the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>or the</hi> Dutch <hi>bee</hi> the affronters, <hi>and</hi> Murtherers.</p>
               <p>That on the 14 of <hi>April,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 1658. the <hi>great Barque</hi> of the <hi>Holland-Weſt-India-Company</hi> coming from <hi>Curaſo,</hi> was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqued in the open Seas, and brought to <hi>Jamaica</hi> by an <hi>Engliſhman of War,</hi> named <hi>Sabado.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Barque</hi> was not only arreſted at <hi>Jamaica</hi> until the 23 of the <hi>ſame month;</hi> but alſo during that time, there was taken from her the ſum of 900 <hi>Livres;</hi> and therefore the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> do demand ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for what they have ſuffered by the ſaid Encounter, and by the retardment of the ſaid <hi>Barque,</hi> and reſtitution of the ſaid 900 <hi>Livres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 15. <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 15.</note> That we have heard that about the time alleadged, there was one <hi>Sabado,</hi> who had Commiſſion to be a <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man of War</hi> from <hi>Lieutenant General Branio,</hi> but knew nothing of any ſuch <hi>Prize</hi> taken by him, or that was brought into <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Company</hi> do ſay, that upon the 29 of <hi>November,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note>1659. one of their <hi>Ships,</hi> named the <hi>St. John,</hi> coming from <hi>Guyne</hi> laden with a conſiderable number of <hi>Slaves,</hi> was put on ſhore near the ſaid <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Curaſo;</hi> and that thoſe of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſo</hi> ſending one of the <hi>Barques</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Company,</hi> (to ſave the ſaid <hi>Slaves</hi>) named the <hi>Oſtridge;</hi> while the men were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to tranſport them from the Ship to the <hi>Barque,</hi> there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48101:21"/>came upon them an <hi>Engliſh Fregat,</hi> called the <hi>Caſtle Fregat,</hi> of which <hi>John Peterſon du Caldican</hi> was <hi>Captain;</hi> who did not onely hinder them from their deſigne, but fell upon them by force, and made himſelf Maſter of them, and took away 84 <hi>blaves</hi> as a lawful <hi>Prize,</hi> and carried them to <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 16.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi> That about the time in the <hi>ſaid Article</hi> mentioned, there was a <hi>Dutch man,</hi> named <hi>Peterſon,</hi> who brought in a <hi>boat</hi> with 6 or 7 <hi>Negroes</hi> to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of more, as he ſaid; and alleadging great ſcarcity of proviſions, did ſell the <hi>Negroes</hi> to the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Jamaica;</hi> and being examined how he came by them, did aver that he took them at <hi>Sea</hi> as a <hi>Wrack;</hi> and the <hi>Carpenter</hi> and <hi>others</hi> of the Ship ſo <hi>wracked,</hi> did juſtify the ſame: All which <hi>depoſitions</hi> were ſent to the <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Curaſſo</hi> by <hi>Col. Doyly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Directors</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Weſt-India-Company</hi> do complain,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> that upon the 12 of <hi>March,</hi> 1660. the <hi>Agents</hi> that they had at <hi>Cabo Verde,</hi> were hindered by <hi>five Engliſh Ships</hi> from Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there, as they had cuſtomarily done; which fruſtrated them of very great advantages and profits, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they remain charged with the Entertainment of their Officers and People, both Military and others, as alſo other Forts, Lodges, Ships, and what depends on them.</p>
               <p>To the 17.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi> That <hi>this Article</hi> is ſo <hi>general,</hi> that no <hi>particular Anſwer</hi> can be made unto it; it making no particular mention of any violence done, nor to whom, except in that <hi>general word</hi> of the <hi>Complaynants Agents</hi> at <hi>Capo de Verde:</hi> And all that can be ſaid, is, that ſome <hi>Ships</hi> in which the <hi>Royal Company</hi> had an <hi>Intereſt,</hi> did about that time paſs to the <hi>River Gambia;</hi> but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48101:21"/>we never heard of any the leaſt violence or injury they did offer to any perſons or Ships in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage thither: And when that <hi>complaint</hi> ſhall be ſo cloathed with <hi>circumſtance,</hi> that we can have any <hi>particular</hi> to ſix upon, an <hi>Anſwer</hi> ſhall be made thereunto.</p>
               <p>In purſuit of this pretence,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> the ſaid <hi>Company</hi> complain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that the ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> after they had thus abuſed them, went to the River of <hi>Gambia,</hi> where they diſpoſſeſt the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of the <hi>Company</hi> with violence and force, and took all, ſo as that people were conſtrained to abandon all the Forts, Lodges, Houſes, and all that the <hi>Company</hi> poſſeſt. And for as much as ſince that time the <hi>Company</hi> hath not been able to Trade, they alledge that the <hi>Damage</hi> they have ſuffered by reaſon hereof ought to be ſufficiently repaired.</p>
               <p>To the 18. <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 18.</note> That it is much of the like nature; for it runs all in <hi>general words,</hi> without naming any <hi>Fort</hi> or <hi>Lodg,</hi> to which the <hi>Dutch Nation</hi> have any <hi>claim,</hi> as we believe will moſt evidently appear, when the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to a particular naming of any <hi>Fort</hi> or <hi>Lodge;</hi> which we have cauſe to think they avoid, leſt the groſſneſs of the allegation ſhould be too notorious.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Company</hi> do further repreſent, that in <hi>Aug.</hi> 1660.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> one of their <hi>Ships,</hi> called the <hi>Peacock,</hi> being at Sea near the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Aruba,</hi> was ſet upon with force by an <hi>Engliſhman of War</hi> and his <hi>Complices,</hi> who brake open the Coffers and Cheſts, and took away what they thought fit, and did very much hurt and outrage, as <hi>declared Enemies</hi> to the <hi>Company</hi> of that Ship; and therefore they do declare, that they may lawfully demand reſtitution for the violences done to them.</p>
               <p>To the 19. <hi>Article,</hi> we <hi>Anſwer;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 19.</note> That the <hi>Man of War,</hi> which the complaynants ſay took their Ship,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48101:22"/>is not named, therefore we cannot <hi>Anſwer;</hi> but we know that about the time mentioned in <hi>this Article,</hi> there was a <hi>Dutch Ship</hi> taken about <hi>Aruba,</hi> by <hi>Capt. Mynges,</hi> which as it appears to the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty,</hi> was in the <hi>ſervice</hi> and <hi>pay</hi> of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> then in hoſtility with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and had ſhot at <hi>Captain Mynges,</hi> and furniſhed the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with <hi>Ammunition,</hi> and had <hi>Spaniards aboard;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore legally condemned by the ſaid <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the end of the year 1660.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> (to wit, the 25 of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>) one of their Ships named the <hi>St. Peter</hi> being at <hi>Anchor</hi> in the <hi>South-Bay,</hi> near the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Cuba</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> was not onely pillaged (to the loſs of her <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> her <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazon,</hi> and all the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils</hi> of the <hi>Ship</hi>) by an <hi>Engliſhman of War,</hi> called the <hi>Pearl, N. Freeborn, Captain;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> in the preſence and ſight of another <hi>Engliſh Ship,</hi> of which <hi>Richard Reesby</hi> was <hi>Commander,</hi> with a Commiſſion of his Majeſties of <hi>England:</hi> but alſo the people of the ſaid Ship were treated in a horrible, and indeed barbarous manner: for among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cruelties which they exerciſed, they put a Cord about the Neck of the <hi>Maſters Mate,</hi> and hung him up in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion till the blood came out at his Noſe and Ears, ſo that the Cord was then cut, thinking he had been dead; after which they put burning Matches to his Fingers, until they had conſumed the fleſh to the bones; and in fine, conſtrained the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Factor</hi> of the ſaid Ship, (as well by the ſad ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, as by horrible threats) to paſs and ſigne an Act, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to approve of all theſe inſolent and inhumane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to avow that the Ship was fair <hi>Prize,</hi> with all her Lading.</p>
               <p>To the 20.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Article,</hi> we <hi>Anſwer;</hi> That it is true, that one <hi>Freeborn,</hi> a <hi>pyrate</hi> (who had no <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> but had formerly been in ſervice of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> and is ſince <hi>taken</hi> by them, and <hi>hang'd</hi> for his <hi>pyracy</hi> at <hi>Cuba</hi>) did plunder ſuch a Ship as is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48101:22"/>in the ſaid <hi>Article;</hi> but coming to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> the then Governour, <hi>Colonel Doyly</hi> apprehended him, and <hi>five others</hi> of his Company, as <hi>pyrates,</hi> and ſent them in <hi>Irons</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> with a <hi>charge</hi> againſt them, and ſecured the reſt of the <hi>pyrates-company</hi> at <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and gave a <hi>Dutch-Maſter</hi> 50 li. to go to <hi>England,</hi> and proſecute the ſaid <hi>pyrates,</hi> and promiſed them paſſage in the <hi>Diamond Fregat;</hi> but for want of <hi>proſecution,</hi> the <hi>pyrates</hi> after 6 <hi>months impriſonment</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were diſcharged, and <hi>Col. Doyly</hi> reſtored the <hi>Ship,</hi> and all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained by her; and furniſhed her with what ſhe wanted to enable her to ſail, out of the <hi>Kings ſtores;</hi> and what ſmall remainder of goods were found belonging to her <hi>Cargo,</hi> the <hi>Colonel</hi> tendred the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to be freely reſtored to him; but he refuſed to accept of them, and there was never any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand made of them ſince; and how freely, and clearly they were dealt with by the ſaid <hi>Governor,</hi> will appear by the following <hi>Copy</hi> of a Letter, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the <hi>Supra Cargo</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Dutch Ship,</hi> upon the <hi>firſt notice</hi> of the <hi>Pyracy</hi> committed.</p>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Jamaica,</hi> 
                        <date>20th of <hi>January,</hi> 1660.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>To <hi>Henry Hamburk, Merchant</hi> of the Ship of <hi>St. Peeter</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> Theſe.</head>
                  <p>WHereas certain goods belonging to you, have been <hi>pyratically</hi> taken, and brought into this <hi>Harbor,</hi> and found out by my labor and induſtry;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48101:23"/>I do according to the <hi>14. Article</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation</hi> between <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces;</hi> offer you your <hi>Ship, Tackle, Arms, Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and <hi>Apparel,</hi> as alſo all ſuch goods as are in being, and found out, that ſo ſuch Juſtice may be done, for and on your behalf, as lies in my power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Liſt <hi>of the</hi> Pretenſions <hi>which the</hi> Inhabitants <hi>and</hi> Subjects <hi>of the</hi> United Provinces <hi>of the</hi> Low Countries <hi>have put in</hi> Writing, <hi>and produc'd againſt the</hi> State, <hi>or ſome</hi> Particular Subjects <hi>of the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Great Britain, <hi>for the</hi> Injuries <hi>and</hi> Damages <hi>which the</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants <hi>and</hi> Subjects <hi>of the ſaid</hi> Provinces <hi>have ſuffered, as well by the</hi> Attaque, Prize <hi>and</hi> Pillage <hi>of their</hi> Veſſels <hi>and</hi> Goods, <hi>as otherwiſe, in other manner, ſince the</hi> year 165 3/4. <hi>in ſeveral parts of the world; and ſince the</hi> year 165 8/9. <hi>in the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>to be repaired according to the</hi> Tenor <hi>of the</hi> 15 Article <hi>of the</hi> Treaty <hi>laſt concluded.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHilip Vanhulten,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and his <hi>aſſociates, Merchants</hi> dwelling in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> do ſay, that in the year 1657. they had freighted a <hi>Ship</hi> named the <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> (<hi>John Lynen</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) to go from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to the <hi>Canaries,</hi> and from <hi>thence</hi> to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> belonging to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and from thence to return to the <hi>Canaries,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Cadiz</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and finally to return to <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> That the ſaid Ship after ſhe had made her <hi>Weſt-India Voyage,</hi> and returned with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48101:23"/>her <hi>Lading</hi> to the <hi>Canaries;</hi> where the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Ship ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found the Orders of the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten,</hi> and of the reſt of the <hi>Owners,</hi> went from thence with his Ship to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> where the ſaid Maſter being arrived in <hi>November</hi> 1658. and beginning to apprehend leſt the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> might give him ſome trouble, he ſteered his courſe for <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> and there he met the <hi>Ship</hi> call'd the <hi>Pro Patria,</hi> whereof <hi>Jacob Muts</hi> was <hi>Master;</hi> whom he thought good to entruſt with the <hi>Hides,</hi> and other <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his <hi>Veſſel</hi> to <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> That while the ſaid Maſter of the Ship was buſie in the Lading of the <hi>Hides</hi> from one Ship to another, there came upon him one of the <hi>Parliaments Ships,</hi> called the <hi>Fairfax,</hi> commanded by <hi>Robert Story,</hi> of the <hi>Squadron</hi> of <hi>General John Stoaks,</hi> which aſſaulted and took thoſe two <hi>Ships,</hi> and carried them to the Coaſt of <hi>Barbary:</hi> and being there, the ſaid <hi>Robert Story</hi> unladed all the Goods out of the Ship <hi>Pro Patria,</hi> and carried them away to <hi>Toulon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> together with the Ship <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> with all her Lading, (as ſhe came from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi>) which conſiſted of 13897 <hi>Hides,</hi> 1384 <hi>Cargoes</hi> of <hi>Cacao,</hi> 2225 <hi>Rolls</hi> of <hi>Tobacco,</hi> 772 pieces of <hi>Brazil Wood,</hi> 18 <hi>Kintals</hi> of <hi>Ginger.</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten</hi> and his Aſſociates having complained thereof to the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> did obtain a diſcharge of the ſaid <hi>Merchandizes</hi> upon <hi>caution;</hi> and accordingly on the 11 of <hi>December</hi> 1660. they obtained <hi>ſentence,</hi> by which the <hi>caution</hi> was <hi>diſcharged,</hi> and the <hi>Goods</hi> declared <hi>free,</hi> adjudging reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution thereof to the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten,</hi> or to his <hi>Aſſignes.</hi> But in ſtead of reſtitution in full, the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten</hi> received ſhort of his due, 2095 <hi>Hides,</hi> 27963 pounds of <hi>Cacao,</hi> 4360 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>Tobacco,</hi> 4722 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>Brazil Wood,</hi> and 1813 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>Ginger.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> exhibited by the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis Complaint</hi> doth Anſwer it ſelf;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 21.</note> that upon complaint to the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> be obtained a <hi>diſcharge of the ſaid Merchandizes; upon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48101:24"/>caution,</hi> and on the 11 of <hi>December,</hi> 1660. he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>ſentence</hi> of <hi>Reſtitution;</hi> whereby his <hi>caution</hi> was <hi>diſcharged,</hi> and the <hi>Merchandizes</hi> declared <hi>free;</hi> condemning thoſe that had detained them, to reſtore them: Now, if all the merchandizes came not to his hand, that were in the Ship, (as he ſaith they did not) yet is there not to be found in the <hi>Admiralty</hi> any <hi>complaint</hi> thereof, nor any proof made upon any ſuch <hi>complaint</hi> of the <hi>reality</hi> or <hi>truth</hi> thereof; ſo that here can be no cauſe of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint</hi> of the defect of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> he himſelf not <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting</hi> any farther to have the <hi>ſentence</hi> put in <hi>execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Mumma,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Huter Peterſon,</hi> and <hi>Gilbert Skouten,</hi> (all Merchants of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and intereſted in the ſaid Ship, the <hi>Maria</hi>) referring themſelves to what hath been alledged by the ſaid <hi>Philip Vanhulten,</hi> and his <hi>Parteners</hi> concerning the ſaid Ship; do ſay further for a ground of their <hi>complaint,</hi> That the ſame Ship was ſtopt at <hi>Toulon</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>three years</hi> and <hi>five moneths;</hi> and that during all that time, the <hi>Owners</hi> could not make any benefit of their <hi>Stock,</hi> nor yet get the Ship diſcharged. And for as much as by the <hi>ſentence</hi> of the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> of the 5th of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1660. it was declared, that the ſaid Ship being wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken, ought to be reſtored to the <hi>Owner,</hi> (as in effect it was, after a tedious purſuit) they think that they have very good grounds to demand <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for all their <hi>Expences, Damages,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts,</hi> beſide the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of their <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as to the <hi>complaint</hi> of <hi>William Mumma,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Huter Peterſon, Gilbert Skouten, Merchants</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> intereſſed in the ſaid Ship, the <hi>Mary:</hi> They complain of an <hi>arreſt</hi> laid upon the ſaid Ship at <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and that they lay under that <hi>arreſt</hi> for the ſpace
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48101:24"/>of 3 <hi>years,</hi> and 5 <hi>months,</hi> and that during that time, the <hi>owners</hi> could not make uſe of their <hi>Stock,</hi> and that the <hi>reſtitution</hi> being made after long perſuits, they think themſelves <hi>well grounded</hi> to demand <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for all their <hi>expenſes</hi> and <hi>damages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>arreſt laid upon the Ship</hi> at <hi>Toulon,</hi> it is neither ſaid <hi>when,</hi> nor by <hi>whom;</hi> ſo that we know not the meaning of it, or why any ſatisfaction for any damages ſuſtained by any <hi>arreſt</hi> at <hi>Toulon,</hi> ſhould be demanded from <hi>England:</hi> And as for the <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> and <hi>expenſes</hi> ſuſtained by the <hi>ſuit depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here:</hi> If there was <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> of the <hi>ſeizure,</hi> then was there <hi>no cauſe</hi> of the giving them <hi>dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> or <hi>expenſes;</hi> If there was <hi>no cauſe</hi> of the <hi>ſeizure,</hi> and the <hi>damage</hi> and <hi>expenſes demanded</hi> at the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>ſentence,</hi> and not <hi>given</hi> they might have <hi>appealed,</hi> and have had <hi>remedy,</hi> but now it is too late.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Philip Vanhulten</hi> doth repreſent farther,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> that one of his <hi>Correſpondents</hi> in <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> (having bought at a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſale 507 <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Galles</hi>) laded the ſame in the Ship called the <hi>Campien, Peter Johnſon Veltmuys</hi> Maſter, and conſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> That the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> being arriv'd, and about to unlade the ſaid <hi>Galles</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Lading,</hi> there came upon him one <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Lowe,</hi> as being empowered from Sir <hi>Andrew Richaut,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the <hi>Levant Trade</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who under a far ſetch'd and frivolous pretence, cauſed the ſaid quantity of <hi>Galles</hi> to be ſeized: And for as much as fince, by a ſentence of the <hi>Schepen</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> of the 7 of <hi>February,</hi> 1653. the ſame <hi>ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure</hi> was declared to be <hi>injurious,</hi> and the Acter thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to reſtore the ſame, with the expences, damages and intereſt; and alſo that during the time of the ſaid ſeizure, the price of <hi>Galles</hi> was much faln, they pretend to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnified.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48101:25"/>
               <p>To the 23.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi> That if the <hi>Sebepen</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> diſcharged the <hi>arreſt,</hi> and <hi>condemned</hi> the <hi>Arreſtant</hi> in <hi>coſt, damage,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> the ſame Court ought to have taxed it, and the Complaynant to proſecute the <hi>Execution</hi> there, while the perſon was upon the place; and may not ſeek ſatisfaction here: But the <hi>Judges</hi> knew very well, that thoſe goods were part of the <hi>charges</hi> of <hi>two Engliſh Ships,</hi> the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and <hi>Free-trade,</hi> that were attaqued by a <hi>Holland Ship,</hi> the <hi>Mary</hi> under the <hi>Hollands Flag,</hi> and taken by a <hi>Spaniſh Commiſſion,</hi> contrary to a <hi>ſecurity</hi> given by <hi>the owners</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Ship of War,</hi> before her departure from <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> that ſhe ſhould not diſturb nor preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice any <hi>Engliſh Subjects</hi> within one <hi>year</hi> from that time; ſo as it is likely, thoſe <hi>Judges</hi> thought it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough at that time, to let their <hi>fellow-burger</hi> remain in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of what was <hi>pyratically</hi> taken, and not to puniſh the <hi>Arreſtants</hi> farther, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding what was their own: And this <hi>complaint</hi> of <hi>Vanhultens,</hi> will finde its deciſion in the ajuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>general demand</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of the whole <hi>lading</hi> of <hi>both Ships,</hi> which his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s <hi>Envoy extraordinary</hi> is, and hath been ever ſince in perſuit of.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Vanhulten,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> do further repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, That although in the year 1655. the King of <hi>Spain</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in <hi>hoſtility</hi> with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> iſſued out a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere <hi>Prohibition</hi> againſt the entrance of any <hi>Ships,</hi> or <hi>Goods</hi> from either of thoſe Kingdomes, into any of the <hi>Ports</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever of his <hi>Catholick Majeſty;</hi> yet his ſaid <hi>Majeſty</hi> diſpenſing for a while to his Subjects the rigour of that <hi>Inhibition,</hi> was pleaſed to permit a <hi>Commerce</hi> with the <hi>French,</hi> ſuffering them to enter his Ports both with their <hi>Ships</hi> and <hi>Merchandizes:</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:48101:25"/>And that the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> building upon that <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> cauſed to be bought at <hi>Rouen,</hi> the ſame year, 69 <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Linnen,</hi> and laded them in the <hi>Ship</hi> call'd the <hi>Hare in the Field, (John Kin, Maſter)</hi> to carry them from <hi>Havredeſrace,</hi> to <hi>Cadiz</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> That in <hi>June</hi> 1665. the ſaid Ship purſuing her Voyage, was aſſaulted, taken, and carried to <hi>London,</hi> by a <hi>Squadron</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Ships,</hi> under pretence that ſhe was a <hi>French Veſſel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> reclaiming their Goods, made it evidently appear that they did not belong to <hi>French-men,</hi> but were onely bought in <hi>France</hi> upon their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, and ſo charg'd, and addreſſed to <hi>Cadiz:</hi> which being prov'd to the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> the ſaid Court being fully ſatisfied as to the matter of Fact, did by a ſentence of the 23 of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1665. diſcharge the ſaid Goods, as having been ſeized againſt all Right and Reaſon.</p>
               <p>That immediately after the ſaid <hi>ſentence</hi> given, the ſaid Merchandizes were again laden, and the ſaid Ship reſumed her courſe to <hi>Cadiz.</hi> But in the mean time, the <hi>Term</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Permiſſion</hi> or <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> being <hi>expired;</hi> the ſaid Ship co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> was there <hi>ſeized</hi> and <hi>confiſcated,</hi> with all her Lading, <hi>July</hi> the 30. 1665.</p>
               <p>Now in regard that all theſe Diſorders happened onely in conſequence of this vexatious and perverſe manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and from that <hi>Delay</hi> which was but an effect thereof, the time of freedome being ſo far ſpent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Diſpute, that it was impoſſible to finiſh the Voyage before it was out; They have reaſon to demand to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>ſecond complaint</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 24.</note> in the 24. <hi>Article;</hi> we find by the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty Court,</hi> the Ship, <hi>the Hare in the field,</hi> with all her Merchandizes (except thoſe that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for lawful prize) were the ſame year re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and that the owners of the ſaid Ship could have no expenſes, nor damages, ſhe being taken with an <hi>enemies goods</hi> in her, which was juſt cauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48101:26"/>enough for the taking and ſeizing of her, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaac Fawquier,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> do ſay, that it is true, that <hi>one</hi> of their Ships named the <hi>Cavillia,</hi> (<hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Balthenſen,</hi> Maſter) did lade the 13 of <hi>January,</hi> 1658. in the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> 2756 <hi>Salmes</hi> of <hi>Wheat</hi> to carry to <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia,</hi> at the rate of 11 <hi>Ryals freight</hi> for each <hi>Salme;</hi> and that withal he had taken on board his Ship a <hi>Spaniſh Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs,</hi> with a quantity of baggage, that he had promiſed to carry for 600 <hi>Ryals of</hi> 8. That the ſaid Ship being arrived at <hi>Valentia,</hi> and buſie in unlading her Wheat, there arrived in in the ſame road <hi>three Engliſh ſhips,</hi> commanded by <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain John Stoakes,</hi> who took the ſaid Ship, with part of the <hi>Wheat</hi> not yet unladen, and with the <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Baggage</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Spaniſh Marqueſs,</hi> carried them to <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Maſter any thing for his <hi>Freight;</hi> neither did the <hi>Engliſh Commander</hi> make him ſatisfaction for the <hi>retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of his <hi>Voyage,</hi> nor for the <hi>Wages</hi> of his <hi>Seamen</hi> for that time.</p>
               <p>To the 25.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 25, 27.</note> and 27. <hi>Articles,</hi> we <hi>Anſwer;</hi> That the Ships were taken by <hi>Capt. Stoaks,</hi> in the time of an open War between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and that the <hi>complaynants</hi> do not ſay but their <hi>goods</hi> were <hi>contra banda,</hi> and <hi>good prize;</hi> and therefore it is conceived there could be no pretence to the <hi>Freight,</hi> for the <hi>Ships</hi> were likewiſe forfeited; and if they had them <hi>freed,</hi> it was of <hi>Grace,</hi> much more if any <hi>freight</hi> was paid them, and therefore they ought to give thanks, and not complain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Rombouts Merchant</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith, that one of his Ships named the <hi>Golden Royal,</hi> of which <hi>Cornelius Isbrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Smit</hi> was Maſter, belonging to <hi>Flyland,</hi> was taken in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> 1661. near the <hi>Dogger Sand,</hi> by a <hi>Scotch Man of War,</hi> (the <hi>Capt.</hi> called <hi>Wutworth</hi>) and brought to <hi>Leith</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48101:26"/>and that the ſaid Ship being <hi>reclaim'd</hi> by the <hi>Proprietors,</hi> who made great and ſeriours Endeavours with his Majeſty the King of <hi>England,</hi> he was pleaſed to order the delivery of the ſaid Ship in <hi>October</hi> next following: but immediately after the releaſe of the ſaid Ship, ſhe being in diſorder, the <hi>Master</hi> repaired and fitted her with <hi>Guns, Victuals, Artillery, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,</hi> and all other neceſſaries: And ſhe being ready to ſayl into <hi>Holland,</hi> his Majeſty was pleaſed to <hi>revoke</hi> the <hi>Releaſe</hi> he had made; whereupon the Magiſtrate of <hi>Edinburg</hi> made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again Maſter of the ſaid Ship by force, and the advantage of the night, and turned out the <hi>Maſter</hi> and all the <hi>Seamen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Proprietors</hi> having repreſented this to his Majeſty, did in the end obtain a <hi>ſecond diſcharge,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1662. the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Ship hoping after this to enjoy the full effect of his <hi>Order,</hi> was forced to content <hi>Captain Wutworth,</hi> and to fit out the Ship again, after ſhe had been the ſecond time plundered.</p>
               <p>To the 26. <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 26.</note> That we never heard of any <hi>Scotch Man of War,</hi> called <hi>Wutworth;</hi> but true it is, that his Majeſty upon the firſt complaint, did write a peremptory <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Privy Council</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Being informed that there are</hi> 2. Veſſels <hi>belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the</hi> States <hi>of the</hi> United Provinces, <hi>the</hi> one <hi>named the</hi> Vogukay, <hi>and the</hi> other, <hi>the</hi> Goude Real; <hi>and a</hi> Buſſe <hi>taken ſome of our Subjects: Our will and pleaſure is, that you command them to be forthwith reſtored unto the hands of</hi> James Davidſon, <hi>or to the</hi> Maſters <hi>of the ſame Ships who are now in</hi> Scotland, <hi>to require them: and withal, that expreſs order be given, that none of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects preſume, upon whatſoever</hi> Pretext <hi>or</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>to take or moleſt any Ship or Boat belonging to the ſaid</hi> States, <hi>under all</hi> higheſt pains. <hi>This</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48101:27"/>Letter was dated the 21. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1661.</p>
               <p>There was <hi>another Letter</hi> written by his Majeſty, 5 <hi>July,</hi> 1662. directed to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Middleton,</hi> then his Majeſties <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> making mention of his former Letter, and then adding;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſoon after, upon an humble</hi> Petition <hi>preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to</hi> Us, <hi>and our</hi> Privy Council <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>by ſome pretending intereſt in the ſaid Ships: We ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed our</hi> Council <hi>to examine the Truth of what was alleadged, and to certifie the ſame to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; and in the mean time, to cauſe the ſaid Ships, with all their materials, to be ſecured till our farther pleaſure. And now, they having examined the whole buſineſs, and having reported the ſame to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, upon conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the whole matter: We do require you, that the ſaid</hi> 2. Veſſels, <hi>with all their</hi> materials, <hi>be fourth-with reſtored to</hi> James Davidſon, <hi>or to the</hi> Maſters <hi>of the ſaid</hi> Ships, <hi>who do attend to receive them: Of which, expecting your performance, We bid you farewel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> of <hi>Edinborough</hi> did any violence; or that the <hi>Maſter</hi> was conſtrained to content <hi>Capt. Wutworth</hi> after the Ship had been a ſecond time plundered, was never complained of to his Majeſty, and therefore is not like to be <hi>true.</hi> And ſeeing the King did ſo readily order <hi>reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it ſeems a groundleſs complaint.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Mumma,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> Merchants of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> do ſay, that one of their <hi>ſhips</hi> named the <hi>Hercules,</hi> (<hi>David Wouters,</hi> Maſter) departing from St. <hi>Sebaſtians, anno</hi> 1657. to go to St. <hi>Lucar</hi> and <hi>Cadiz,</hi> was the 14 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the <hi>ſame year,</hi> taken and detained by the ſaid Captain <hi>John Stoakes,</hi> who took out all the <hi>Merchandize</hi> laden upon her,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48101:27"/>without giving him any reaſonable ſatisfaction for his <hi>Freight;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this, <hi>pag.</hi> 44.</note> onely that the ſaid <hi>Commander</hi> paid him 1500 <hi>Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of</hi> 8. and no more. The ſaid <hi>Mumma</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> do pretend that they ought to be re-imburſed of their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, Damages</hi> and <hi>Intereſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albert Lemmerman</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſays, that in <hi>Octob.</hi> 1655.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> one of the ſhips named the <hi>St. James,</hi> of the burthen of 300 <hi>Tuns,</hi> (<hi>Aaron Martin,</hi> Maſter) coming from <hi>Porto</hi> in <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> laden with <hi>Tobacco, Sugars, Shumack,</hi> and <hi>Elephants Teeth,</hi> having ſprung a Leak at Sea by <hi>foul weather,</hi> and being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made incapable of proſecuting her Voyage; the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Ship (to avoid a further danger) ran aſhore upon the Coaſt of <hi>Arundel;</hi> and being there buſie in unlading the Ship of ſome of her choiceſt Goods, an Officer came to him, and commanded him preſently to leave his Ship, not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to carry any thing away with him. That the ſaid <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Mariners</hi> being thus conſtrained to leave the ſaid Ship and Goods, there fell upon them preſently a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Country people, who by the <hi>order,</hi> or at leaſt with the <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>Officer,</hi> pillaged the Ship, carried away all the <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> and took away the <hi>Cordage, Rigging,</hi> and all to the very <hi>bolts</hi> and <hi>nails,</hi> leaving the very <hi>hulk</hi> of the Ship worth nothing. And though the ſaid Maſter made his complaint of this barbarous proceeding, and in perſuit of the buſineſs ſpent a great deal of his time and money; and though the <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>State</hi> and the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were fully convinced of the reaſon of his complaint; yet ſo it is, that the ſaid <hi>Lemmerman</hi> could never obtain the leaſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, either by way of <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> but was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually put off with delays and excuſes.</p>
               <p>As to the 28. <hi>Article,</hi> it is <hi>Anſwered;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 28.</note> That it may be very well ſo; and the parties may eſcape with ſo foul an Act, unleſs a <hi>complaint</hi> had been made againſt ſome <hi>particular perſons</hi> of them by <hi>name,</hi> that they might have been proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and proſecuted according to the Law of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48101:28"/>
                  <hi>Admiralty,</hi> which hath certain Rules to proceed by againſt ſuch Offendors; yet we do find in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> a complaint entered; upon which a <hi>commiſſion</hi> of <hi>Inquiry,</hi> iſſued forth for diſcovery of ſuch perſons as had done ſuch violence, but can find no return thereof, ſo that it ſeemeth no ſuch diſcovery could be made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Pouilly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Preten. Art. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jerome Boſhe,</hi> the <hi>Widow</hi> of <hi>Heertgen Johnſon,</hi> the <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>Daniel Johnſon,</hi> Merchants of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> do all ſay, that it is very true, that one of their Ships named the St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> (of which Baron <hi>Claeſsen Spierdyck</hi> was Maſter) co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in <hi>January</hi> 1657. from the <hi>Iſle</hi> of St. <hi>Vincent,</hi> was taken by an <hi>Engliſh Fregat</hi> call'd the <hi>Mackdethem,</hi> and was delivered to <hi>Admiral Blake:</hi> That the ſame Ship being carried to <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> was there unladen of all her Merchandize, part whereof was ſent to <hi>London,</hi> and the reſt ſold with the Ship it ſelf at <hi>Lisbon.</hi> The ſame Ship and goods being reclaimed by the ſaid Merchants in the month of <hi>December</hi> in the ſame year, 1657. after long and painful purſuits, the ſaid Goods were declared free and exempt from all confiſcation, by two ſucceſſive ſentences of the <hi>High Court of Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> of the 17 of <hi>January,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> on the 20 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1659. That there being made in <hi>England,</hi> an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the proceeding upon the ſale of the ſaid Ship and Goods, it was found to amount to the ſum of 11407 l. 3. s. 9d. <hi>ſterling:</hi> (making 120 <hi>m. Florens</hi>) And foraſmuch as the ſaid Merchants could never enjoy the effects of the ſaid <hi>ſentence,</hi> nor obtain any <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> They pretend that they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>ſame ſumme,</hi> by vertue of the ſaid <hi>ſentence;</hi> with the <hi>Expenſes, Damages,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>complaint</hi> of <hi>Peter Ravilli,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 29.</note> and others, ſet forth in the 29. <hi>Article,</hi> it may receive the ſame Anſwer as is made to the complaint of the ſaid <hi>Vanhulten,</hi> upon the 21 <hi>Article.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48101:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lawrence Kettles,</hi> Merchant of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 30.</note> That in <hi>May</hi> 1659. his Ship named the <hi>King David,</hi> (<hi>Oche Alberts</hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inlopen, Maſter</hi>) laden with <hi>Salt</hi> at St. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>vall,</hi> and bound for <hi>Dronton</hi> in <hi>Norway,</hi> was taken and carried to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> by Captain <hi>Lonis de Hay</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 30. <hi>Article,</hi> We anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 30.</note> that the Captain was neither an <hi>Engliſh Subject,</hi> nor had any <hi>Engliſh Commiſſion,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible for his action.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Johnſon Brunan</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 31.</note> That in the Moneth of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1659. his Ship named the <hi>Black Raven (James John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Vanderſchelling, Maſter)</hi> coming from <hi>Rochel</hi> laden with <hi>Salt</hi> was taken in the <hi>Channel</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh man of Warr,</hi> called <hi>John Jaquerſon hill.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>ship</hi> being brought to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> the Governour releaſed her by order of His Majeſty, but ſhe was afterward ſeized by Order of the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> ſo that the Maſter was conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the purſuit of one <hi>Moneth,</hi> to redeem his Ship with the ſumm of 3333 <hi>Livres</hi> 17 <hi>Solz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the 31. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 31.</note> It is anſwered that the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of the Ship knew his <hi>Ship,</hi> or ſome of her <hi>Lading,</hi> to be ſubject or liable, in ſome reſpect, to <hi>Confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that he voluntarily would ſo redeem her; and <hi>for ſuch voluntary act, no ſatisfaction can be required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Vanderhell</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 32.</note> ſay that it is very true, that in the year 1659. the Ship named the <hi>Salamander (Albert Jaquerſon, Maſter)</hi> coming from <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> to go to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> was attaqued, taken and brought to <hi>Toulon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh man of Warr.</hi> That the <hi>Maſter</hi> and the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> having upon their complaint ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Releaſe, which was adjudged afterwards, That before ſhe ſhould be abſolutely diſcharged, the Intereſſed ſhould furniſh the ſumm of <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> who
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48101:29"/>to get clear of the buſineſs, and to deliver themſelves from this vexation, were neceſſitated to pay the ſaid ſumm for <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Runſome</hi> thereof. That the recovery of the money having been made by that Rule upon the <hi>Goods;</hi> and the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> having paid it at <hi>Toulon,</hi> could not yet obtain the effect of that <hi>Releaſe,</hi> but were diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the <hi>Money,</hi> as alſo of the <hi>Ship</hi> and <hi>Goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 32.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Article,</hi> We ſay that ſeeing the <hi>Captain</hi> complained of, hath <hi>no name,</hi> nor the <hi>ranſome</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be paid for him, any <hi>ſumm,</hi> it may as well be a <hi>Barretry</hi> of the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Salamander,</hi> as an <hi>act</hi> of an <hi>Engliſhman:</hi> but whoſoever he was that took him, and whatſoever he had for compoſition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the owner of the <hi>Salamander</hi> knew he could juſtifie the capture, or they would not have compounded with him in the Ports of the <hi>French</hi> King, their good <hi>Allie,</hi> where they might have had <hi>juſtice</hi> againſt a <hi>Pyrate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benjamin Lanſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 33.</note> the ſon of <hi>Julien Lanſon</hi> deceaſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents that in the year 1655, certain <hi>Parliament ſhips</hi> took away out of the <hi>ſhip</hi> called the <hi>Medea (Horman Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinſe, Maſter)</hi> theſe goods following, 92 <hi>Pipes</hi> of <hi>Oyl,</hi> 283. <hi>Cheſts</hi> of <hi>Soap;</hi> 8. <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Cotten;</hi> 102. <hi>Barrels</hi> of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur;</hi> 14 <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Galls.</hi> All which belonged to the ſaid <hi>Julien Lanſon;</hi> and that the ſaid goods were placed in manner of <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> in the hands of <hi>John Sparrow, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Hill, Richard Blackwell, Samuel Wilſon, Humphrey Blake,</hi> and <hi>Robert Turpin;</hi> being all <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Admiralty</hi> for <hi>Prize good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the 23. of <hi>December</hi> 1657. the very <hi>Admiralty</hi> it ſelf ordered the ſaid <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> to make <hi>reſtitution</hi> of the ſaid <hi>goods,</hi> or of the monies raiſed thereupon, to the ſaid <hi>Julien Lanſon;</hi> But that notwithſtanding a conſtant ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation of three <hi>years</hi> continuance for a diſpatch, the ſaid <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> would not yet be perſwaded to comply with the ſaid <hi>ſentence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48101:29"/>
               <p>That in the year 1660. the ſaid Commiſſioners were the <hi>ſecond time</hi> formally condemned to the ſaid <hi>reſtitution;</hi> there being likewiſe adjudged to the ſaid <hi>Lanſon</hi> upon his accompt then produced, the ſumm of 3385 <hi>pounds</hi> 2 <hi>ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> and 10 <hi>pence, ſterl.</hi> or 36000 <hi>Florens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in regard that the ſaid <hi>Julien</hi> could never receive the benefit either of the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other ſentence,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it now with <hi>charges, damages,</hi> and <hi>intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 33. <hi>Article</hi> we anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer</hi> 33.</note> That the <hi>neat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> of the <hi>goods</hi> therein mentioned, amounted to no more then 1841 <hi>pounds,</hi> and that they themſelves at laſt, left the <hi>diſpute</hi> undetermined: ſo that if they did not receive the fruit they expected from the ſaid <hi>Decree,</hi> they may blame themſelves for not making a more effectual <hi>proſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Belin de la Garde,</hi> Merchant of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Artic.</hi> 34.</note> ſaith that in the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> 1655. ſome ſhips of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi> did carry to <hi>London</hi> a <hi>ſhip</hi> named <hi>the Hare in the Field (John Kin, Maſter:)</hi> and though by <hi>ſentence</hi> of the High Court of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> it was declared, that <hi>three parts</hi> of the Goods ſhould be diſcharged; to wit, 7 <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Linnen,</hi> 1 <hi>Bale of Yellow Linnen,</hi> 4 <hi>Cask of Mercery ware;</hi> all belonging to the ſaid <hi>De la Garde:</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See for the Anſwer to this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe, <hi>pa. 53.</hi>
                  </note> And though in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the ſaid ſentence, moſt of the ſaid Goods were reſtored to him, yet ſo it is, that a great part of thoſe Goods were quite ſpoyled, and the reſt ſo periſhed and damnified, that they loſt much of their juſt value.</p>
               <p>The ſame perſon complains again, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> that one of his ſhips called the <hi>Croſs of Jeruſalem</hi> (<hi>Peter Johnſon Maſter,</hi> Native of <hi>Purmerent</hi>) being ſet upon and taken by a Veſſel of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> was in <hi>June</hi> 1655. carried to <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and in <hi>Auguſt</hi> following, to <hi>London.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>La Guarde</hi> having repreſented (by certain perſons whom he authorized) the injury and violence that had been
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48101:30"/>done to the ſaid ſhip; and having demanded the releaſe thereof, the Court of <hi>Admiralty</hi> finding themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by the force of Reaſon and Truth, did agree to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe her by a <hi>ſentence</hi> of the 18. of <hi>June</hi> 1656. and did Ordain that the ſaid ſhip ſhould be reſtored to the ſaid <hi>De la Garde,</hi> together with the <hi>freight</hi> of the goods that were laden on her, according to the <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Lading</hi> that were produced. And foraſmuch as the ſaid <hi>De la Garde</hi> could not enjoy the effect of the ſaid <hi>ſentence,</hi> but onely in part: And that during the time of <hi>three Moneths,</hi> while they ſaid ſhip lay ſeized, he could not onely make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but was likewiſe obliged to pay the <hi>Seamens</hi> wages, and to entertain them with <hi>Victuals,</hi> undergoing a great expence before he could obtain the <hi>ſentence;</hi> for which he demands to be indemnified. The ſaid <hi>De la Garde</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>intereſſed</hi> not onely in the <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>freight,</hi> but alſo in <hi>two Parcels</hi> the <hi>one</hi> of 65, and <hi>the other</hi> of 3 <hi>Bales</hi> of <hi>Linnen</hi> of <hi>Roan,</hi> did in fine obtain that they might be alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the ſaid <hi>Restitution</hi> adjudged him by <hi>two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſentences,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> of the 25 of <hi>February,</hi> and <hi>the other</hi> of the 4. of <hi>July</hi> 1656. And foraſmuch as all the ſaid Merchandizes were not delivered to the ſaid <hi>De la Garde,</hi> nor to his <hi>Aſſurers,</hi> to whoſe uſe he had made over the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the ſame: And alſo that by the long ſeizure, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchances that happened thereupon, their <hi>value</hi> was <hi>diminiſhed</hi> by <hi>one quarter:</hi> Whereas on the contrary, if the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip had not done them this Injury there had been got at leaſt 30. <hi>per cent.</hi> ſo that the ſaid <hi>Complainant</hi> doth believe that he may demand to be <hi>Indemnified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>De la Garde</hi> doth complain that one of his ſhips called the <hi>Golden Fortune (Francis Johnſon</hi> of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Maſter</hi>) was taken in <hi>July</hi> 1655. and carried to <hi>Poully</hi> by Captain <hi>Green,</hi> being then in Commiſſion and under Oath to the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and foraſmuch as the ſaid <hi>De la Garde</hi> did make it evidently to appear, that when the ſaid ſhip was taken and reclaimed, the <hi>propriety</hi> was ſolely in himſelf: and that the ſaid Captain had extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> by vertue of which he could not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48101:30"/>
                  <hi>Arm</hi> himſelf but againſt the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the King of <hi>France.</hi> The ſaid <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty</hi> by their <hi>ſentence</hi> of the 28. of <hi>July</hi> 1655. did not onely decree a full releaſe of the ſaid ſhip, but did alſo order, That the ſaid <hi>Henry Green</hi> and all others, ſhould reſtore the ſaid ſhip with her apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinences, without any reſerve; and alſo to pay to the <hi>Owners</hi> the <hi>freight</hi> which the Maſter of the ſaid ſhip was to have had for the <hi>carriage</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Goods</hi> that were found aboard her, and taken by the ſaid <hi>Henry Green.</hi> And though according to the ſaid <hi>ſentence,</hi> the ſaid <hi>reſtitution</hi> ought to have been effective, and the payment made; yet ſo it is, that the ſaid <hi>freight</hi> was not <hi>paid,</hi> nor the <hi>ſhip reſtored</hi> until they had taken away, and pillaged more of what did belong to her.</p>
               <p>The ſame perſon doth further complain,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 37.</note> That in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1655. one of his ſhips named the <hi>St. James</hi> (<hi>Peter John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam, Maſter</hi>) returning from the <hi>Maderas</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> was aſſaulted, taken, and carried to <hi>Dover,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captain (<hi>Edward Goodwin</hi> by vertue of a Commiſſion from <hi>England.</hi> That the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> being duly informed of the injuſtice of the <hi>Prize,</hi> did give releaſe to the ſaid ſhip, and by a <hi>ſentence</hi> of the 28. of <hi>November,</hi> 1655. ordered the ſaid <hi>Edward Goodwin</hi> to make ſpeedy and full reſtitution, which was not done; and the ſaid <hi>De la Garde</hi> did not enjoy the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſaid <hi>ſentence,</hi> but onely in part; the reſtitution having been made by little and little, in <hi>four Moneths</hi> time, and therefore he demands his damages.</p>
               <p>To the 34, 35, 36, and 37. <hi>Articles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw. to</hi> 34, 35, 36. &amp; 37. <hi>Art.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> therein contained, are to be anſwered as to the <hi>complaints</hi> of <hi>Van Hulten,</hi> ſet forth in the 21 <hi>Article; viz.</hi> that there is no <hi>complaint</hi> entered in the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty</hi> that can be found; whereas not onely <hi>complaint,</hi> ought to have been made, but likewiſe <hi>proof</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> of ſuch <hi>complaint,</hi> which being not done, there
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48101:31"/>can be no cauſe of <hi>Complaint</hi> now made of the want of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> himſelf not proſecuting any farther to have the ſaid <hi>Sentence</hi> put in due <hi>Execution.</hi> Nor can they make any <hi>Demand</hi> here, in regard the ſhip was taken in the time when there was <hi>Hoſtility</hi> between <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>L'Guard</hi> being a <hi>French-man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Godfrey Waſſemburgh</hi> dwelling at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 38.</note> complains that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip, commanded by Captain <hi>Chriſtopher Mennys,</hi> did in the Year, 1658. near the <hi>Barbadoes</hi> take the ſhip called the <hi>Charity,</hi> which he carried with her lading to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where he cauſed the ſaid Goods by Order of the <hi>Admiralty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> reſiding in that <hi>Iſland,</hi> to be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and amongſt the reſt, <hi>two Caſes of fine Linnen,</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid <hi>Waſſemburgh.</hi> And further, that ſince <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> who took upon him at that time the Stile of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> knowing that the ſaid <hi>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>Charity</hi> was an <hi>Engliſh Veſſel</hi> ſet out by <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at <hi>London,</hi> and others in this <hi>Country,</hi> to whom the Trade of <hi>Barbadees</hi> was not forbidden, did declare, that the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> in her were free, ſo that a good part of the ſaid <hi>Merchandizes</hi> was reſtord to the owners, Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, the ſaid <hi>Waſſemburgh</hi> could never obtain reſtitution of thoſe <hi>two Caſes</hi> of <hi>fine Linnen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 38. <hi>Article;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> We Anſwer, That it is true, that <hi>Captain Mennys</hi> did take ſuch a ſhip which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards reſtored entire, as it was brought in, ſave only what might be plundered by the <hi>Seamen:</hi> (which no care can prevent) but by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Navigation;</hi> the whole <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> ought to have been <hi>Confiſcated,</hi> but the <hi>Intention</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> was deluded by ſome <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Men,</hi> pretending a <hi>Propriety</hi> in the goods, who never ſince made any demand of the goods menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>this Article.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48101:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Van Wickford,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 39.</note> do complain, that one of their (<hi>ſhips</hi> called <hi>Campen</hi> was attacqued, taken, and carried to <hi>Jamaica</hi> by <hi>Three Engliſh Fregats,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> was ſince releaſed after it was known that it was not laden with any goods of <hi>Contrabanda:</hi> But in the mean while there was taken out of her a Quantity of <hi>goods,</hi> and by reaſon of this ſtop, the <hi>ſhip</hi> could not accompliſh her <hi>Voyage,</hi> for which they demand <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this 39. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> we Anſwer as to the <hi>Preceding Complaint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Van Meekerel</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 40.</note> Proprietours of the <hi>ſhip</hi> called the <hi>Peace,</hi> and of her <hi>Cargazon,</hi> do complain that on the 26 of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1655. the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> having taken in ſome <hi>Slaves</hi> upon the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of <hi>Guyne,</hi> and that ſhe had put them off for <hi>Sugars</hi> at the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> where ſhe had alſo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for <hi>Elephants Teeth,</hi> and other <hi>Merchandize,</hi> was attac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued upon the open <hi>Seas,</hi> and carried to the <hi>Barbadoes</hi> by a <hi>Parliament Veſſel of England,</hi> of the <hi>Squadron of Admiral Penn.</hi> And although the <hi>Interreſſed</hi> made their <hi>Complaint,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Wrongs</hi> that had been done them unto <hi>Cromwell;</hi> which Complaints were from time to time ſeconded by the continual Inſtances of the <hi>Embaſſadours</hi> by <hi>Order</hi> from the <hi>States,</hi> yet ſo it is, that they could never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> neither for <hi>ſhip</hi> nor <hi>goods,</hi> for which they now demand it.</p>
               <p>To the 40. <hi>Article,</hi> we Anſwer, That the ſaid ſhip,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Peace,</hi> was taken as trading contrary to the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>Navigation,</hi> and according to the practiſe of the <hi>Holland West India Company;</hi> who conſtantly give <hi>Letters of Mart</hi> to all their ſhips, to take Veſſels that trade to any of their <hi>Plantations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>John Clawſen Ritſert, Merchants,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 41.</note> dwelling at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> do repreſent, that the ſhips, <hi>Red Lion,</hi> and <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48101:32"/>Port,</hi> upon each of which they had <hi>Enſured</hi> 2000 <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens</hi> departing from <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1661. and arriving at <hi>New found Land,</hi> the 14. of <hi>June</hi> following, were there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by an <hi>Engliſh ſhip of War,</hi> called the <hi>Jerſey; Richard Hacks Captain,</hi> who pillaged her, and took away her beſt, and moſt Valuable Goods and ſent her afterward to <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> And though upon the 5. of <hi>October</hi> following, the ſame <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> were declared <hi>free;</hi> this yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the Reſtitution was not made but in part, the Goods that were taken away remaining in the hands of thoſe that took them. Now foraſmuch as in the Quality of being <hi>Enſured,</hi> they were condemned the 30. of <hi>April</hi> 1661. by two ſeveral <hi>ſentences</hi> of the Commiſſioners for <hi>Sea Affairs,</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> to <hi>re-imburſe,</hi> and <hi>indemnifie</hi> the <hi>intereſſed</hi> in proportion to what they <hi>ſigned,</hi> for the loſs that they have ſuffered upon the ſaid Merchandizes: And that the ſaid loſs hath been ſince valued by <hi>Arbitratours,</hi> upon the <hi>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>Red Lion,</hi> at 44. and the <hi>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>Golden Port,</hi> at 38. <hi>per Cent.</hi> They demand Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>To the 41. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note> We ſay that the ſhip was taken trading contrary to the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Navigation,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Legally Confiſcate;</hi> and if any thing was reſtored; it was of <hi>Grace,</hi> and though the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> might have recourſe upon their <hi>Aſſurers,</hi> who were obliged to Indemnifie the <hi>Aſſured</hi> againſt all kind of <hi>Loſſes,</hi> yet the <hi>Inſurers</hi> had no <hi>colour</hi> of <hi>pretence</hi> againſt the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul Timmers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 42.</note> and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> dwelling at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> do ſay, that one of their ſhips, named the <hi>Stroy Yoncker (Jum Alberts Maſter)</hi> coming for <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> laden with <hi>Wines,</hi> and <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> was in the <hi>month</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1661. <hi>attacqued,</hi> and <hi>taken</hi> near the <hi>Maaz,</hi> and carried to <hi>Dover</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh Captain,</hi> named <hi>John Penny;</hi> and though it were eaſie to make it appear Evidently that the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> were taken from the <hi>Owners,</hi> without <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> ſo that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48101:32"/>they ought to have promiſed <hi>Reſtitution</hi> without delay, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch earneſt and preſſing Inſtances being made for the ſame: And that the <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of this <hi>Action</hi> was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently repreſented to the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> who ought to have taken <hi>Cognizance</hi> of it; Nevertheleſs, the ſaid <hi>Intereſſed,</hi> after they had taken much pains, and been at much expence, were obliged to <hi>Compound</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Captain Penny,</hi> upon very unjuſt Conditions, and to give him 200 l. <hi>sterling,</hi> though the <hi>Wine</hi> were in part <hi>ſpoiled,</hi> and that the reſt had loſt the <hi>half</hi> of its value, after ſo long a time.</p>
               <p>To the 42. <hi>Article,</hi> We ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> That if the <hi>Complaynant</hi> had not the <hi>patience</hi> to attend the <hi>due proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Admiralty,</hi> for a <hi>deciſion</hi> of his <hi>pretended right,</hi> but <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated</hi> it by a <hi>voluntary compoſition,</hi> with the <hi>Captain;</hi> It muſt neceſſarily be concluded that he was <hi>conſcious</hi> of his <hi>guilt,</hi> and therefore durſt not ſtand the <hi>Tryal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon Tunemans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Artic.</hi> 43.</note> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> do <hi>Complain,</hi> that having in <hi>July,</hi> 1662. ſent one of their ſhips named the <hi>Swan,</hi> to the <hi>fiſhing</hi> of <hi>Whales</hi> in <hi>Green-Land,</hi> was hindred from the <hi>beginning</hi> of his <hi>fiſhing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See <hi>58.</hi> for this Anſw.</note> and ſo evilly entreated by an <hi>Engliſh Man of War</hi> that took all his <hi>Shallopps, Cordage,</hi> and <hi>Nets, Oares,</hi> and <hi>Sails,</hi> and all his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Inſtruments; that finding himſelf no longer able to continue his <hi>fiſhing,</hi> he was conſtrained to retire, and return to <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> for which he demands <hi>Indempnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame doth further repreſent,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 44.</note> that another of his ſhips named the <hi>Collier,</hi> (<hi>Gerard Corneliſen</hi> Maſter) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> was taken by an <hi>Engliſh Man of War,</hi> and carried to <hi>Portſmouth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See <hi>59.</hi> for this Anſw.</note> and he alledgeth, that the <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> he received in that <hi>Encounter</hi> ought to be made good to him, <hi>cum omni cauſâ &amp; acceſſione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Van Leith,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 45.</note> dwelling at <hi>Dort.</hi> doe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48101:33"/>repreſent that in the year, 1661. one of their ſhips, called the <hi>Prince William, (John Werbeck</hi> Maſter) being at <hi>Anchor</hi> at the entrance of the <hi>Harbour</hi> at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> under the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Castle,</hi> was attacqued by the <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> and <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> of that place, who took from him his <hi>Sails, Cables, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> and other neceſſaries. That the ſaid <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> not daring to bring the ſaid ſhip into any Harbour, becauſe they knew there was none could approve of the <hi>Pyracy;</hi> extorted from the Maſter of the ſhip, by way of <hi>Ranſom</hi> the ſumm of 26l. 10. <hi>ſhil. sterling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 43,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer to</hi> 43, 44, 45.</note> 44, 45. <hi>Articles,</hi> we can give no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, untill the <hi>Perſons</hi> complained of, be <hi>Named,</hi> and the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> more <hi>Explained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Henry Van Leith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti</hi> 46.</note> and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> ſay yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that on the 2. of <hi>June</hi> following, the ſame ſhip being Arriv'd before the ſame Harbour of <hi>Plymouth</hi> was again At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqued by a Captain, named <hi>Stephen Evers,</hi> apparently at the Inſtigation of the ſaid <hi>Burgers;</hi> who took him and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and though they made the moſt Active Inſtances, and all poſſible endeavours for it, yet ſo it is, that they could not obtain the Reſtitution of the <hi>ſhip</hi> or <hi>Merchandizes,</hi> nor the <hi>value</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> or of the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 46. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That Stephen Evers</hi> was no <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Man,</hi> nor had any <hi>Engliſh Commiſsion,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot Anſwer for <hi>Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Proprietours</hi> of the ſhip named the <hi>steeple of Dort,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 47.</note> as alſo <hi>Jacob Vandergraff, Iſaac Bieſheuvel,</hi> and their <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> as <hi>Freightours,</hi> and <hi>Proprietours</hi> of the goods, do ſay, that the ſaid ſhip being ſunk at <hi>Harwich,</hi> the <hi>Burgers</hi> of the <hi>Town,</hi> and the <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the <hi>Garriſon</hi> of the Caſtle, inſtead of ſuccouring and comforting the <hi>Master</hi> of the ſaid ſhip in his misfortune, as they were obliged, did cut his <hi>Sails</hi> and <hi>Cordage,</hi> and put him quite out of condition to ſet ſail; and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48101:33"/>after this, they pillag'd his <hi>ſhip,</hi> and took away the goods that were laden upon her; ſo that the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> could not recover any thing, neither in <hi>part,</hi> nor in <hi>whole,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the endeavours they uſed; ſo that it cannot be denyed but that they ought to be <hi>Indemnified,</hi> with <hi>Coſts,</hi> and <hi>Interests.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 47. <hi>Article,</hi> That no <hi>time</hi> is <hi>mentioned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> nor <hi>perſons named</hi> that are complained of; nor is it <hi>alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that any <hi>Appeal</hi> was made for <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Pychen, Theodore Van herweere,</hi> and their <hi>Aſſociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 48.</note> all <hi>Merchants,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Dort,</hi> do ſay, that one of their ſhips called the <hi>Prince,</hi> whereof <hi>(Laurence Davids Captain)</hi> who was taken near the <hi>Caribes,</hi> by <hi>five Engliſh ſhips,</hi> and brought to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> under pretence that the ſaid <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Davids</hi> might diſcover the deſign the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had to ſurprize the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Jamaica.</hi> And foraſmuch as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, the ſaid ſhip could not finiſh her Voyage, they thereby loſt the profit which they did infallibly believe to make, as well upon the <hi>Cargaſon,</hi> as upon the <hi>Return;</hi> and on the <hi>contrary,</hi> by that hinderance, they ſuffered great <hi>Loſſes,</hi> and pretend to be <hi>Indemnified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 48. <hi>Article,</hi> It is Anſwered,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> That the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainant</hi> doth not affirm that ever he made any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> nor have we any <hi>Evidence</hi> that he <hi>received</hi> any <hi>Injury,</hi> and therefore we think the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> to be <hi>frivolous,</hi> and out of time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albert Arentſen, Merchant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 49.</note> dwelling at the <hi>Brill</hi> complains that about the <hi>middle</hi> of <hi>Sep</hi> 1659, a bark of his ſerving for the <hi>fiſhing</hi> of <hi>Herrings</hi> did meet between the <hi>Maaz,</hi> and the <hi>Sea,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh ſhip,</hi> commanded by one <hi>Captain Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who in a <hi>frolick,</hi> without any offence in any manner offered him, <hi>Boarded</hi> him, <hi>took</hi> him, and carried him to <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:48101:34"/>
               <p>To the 49.51,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 52, 53, 54, 56, 61, 62, 63, 64, 68, 70, 71, 72. We Affirm the ſeveral Actions therein mentioned, were not done by <hi>Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions;</hi> and if they were done by any <hi>Foraign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions, Portugal, Swedes,</hi> or any <hi>Other;</hi> we are no more reſponſible for them, then the <hi>Hollanders</hi> would be for thoſe <hi>Hundred Ships</hi> and their <hi>Charges</hi> that were taken by <hi>Hollands Ships,</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>Spaniſh Commiſsions,</hi> in the time of the <hi>late Warr</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>the King of Spain,</hi> and <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leonard Licoghton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 50.</note> and <hi>John Ham, Merchants,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Enchuyſen,</hi> do complain that in <hi>August.</hi> 1660. an <hi>Engliſh Captain,</hi> (called <hi>George Wotworth</hi>) did ſeize at <hi>Haymouth</hi> near <hi>Berwick,</hi> and carried away, <hi>two</hi> ſhips for <hi>Herring fiſhing</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them. The <hi>One,</hi> the <hi>Prince of Aurange</hi> (<hi>Femme Claeſſen</hi> Maſter) and the <hi>Other,</hi> the <hi>Three Golden Herrings,</hi> Commanded by the <hi>Master-Mate, Peter Johnſon,</hi> which were unladen, and their <hi>Cargaſon</hi> ſent to <hi>London,</hi> where it was ſold; It is true, that after great inſtance and long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitation, the Commander of <hi>Haymouth,</hi> did releaſe the ſaid ſhips, and referred them to <hi>Captain Bronſert,</hi> of <hi>Mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedam,</hi> but they never got the reſt, nor ſatisfaction for the <hi>Herrings, Netts, Cordage, Anchors, Victualls,</hi> and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries of the ſhips which were utterly loſt; as alſo a 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>part</hi> of the ſaid ſhips, which was condemned by the <hi>High-Court of Admiralty</hi> of the <hi>North-Holland,</hi> as an <hi>acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and that without prejudice to the <hi>Charge</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Captains</hi> have been at to bring home the ſhips into their Country.</p>
               <p>To the 50. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> We never <hi>heard</hi> of the <hi>Two Ships</hi> therein named, and <hi>leſs</hi> of the <hi>Men,</hi> called <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners</hi> of <hi>Haymouth,</hi> who are ſaid to have releaſed them. <hi>Haymouth</hi> being a very ſmall <hi>Village,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Dozen</hi> or <hi>Sixteen Fiſher-Mens Hovells.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:48101:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leonard Licoghton,</hi> and <hi>John Ham,</hi> do repreſent further,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 51.</note> that in the Year 1659. one of their ſhips, namely the <hi>Forest,</hi> (<hi>Herman Janſſen</hi> of <hi>Enchuyſen, Master</hi>) was attacqued, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,<note place="margin" type="runSum">See for the Anſwer to theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes, <hi>pa. 60.</hi>
                  </note> carried away, and ſold, at <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh Man of War</hi> and that the ſhip was likewiſe ſold with her <hi>Herrings, Salt, Caske,</hi> and other neceſſary <hi>Inſtruments</hi> for <hi>fiſhing,</hi> to one <hi>George England Alderman</hi> of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in the ſaid <hi>Man of War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame perſon ſaith further,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 52.</note> that in the year 1660. the ſame <hi>Man of War, (Wotworth)</hi> took one of his <hi>Barques</hi> at the <hi>Herring-fiſhing,</hi> named the <hi>Faith, (Cornelius Barentſon Kelocker Master)</hi> and carried it to <hi>Montroſs</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Peterſon, (Masters Mate)</hi> dwelling at <hi>Enchuyſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 53.</note> complains that in the Year 1659 he was taken with his ſhip named the <hi>Green Tree, fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Herrings,</hi> laden with ſeven <hi>Last</hi> and a half of <hi>Herrings,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh ſhip,</hi> of which the <hi>Captain</hi> was called <hi>Cooler,</hi> who carried him to <hi>Ely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roemer Cant, Burgomaster,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Moſſel, Schepen</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chuyſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 54.</note> do repreſent, that in <hi>September</hi> 1655. a <hi>Man of Warr</hi> that went from <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and was <hi>mann'd</hi> from <hi>Thence,</hi> took <hi>Two</hi> of their <hi>ſhips</hi> upon the Sea, <hi>fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Herrings,</hi> the <hi>One</hi> named the St. <hi>Peter,</hi> of which (<hi>Reyn Engëlſe</hi> of <hi>Egmont</hi> was Maſter.) And the <hi>Other</hi> named the <hi>Turtle,</hi> (of which <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Janſſen</hi> was Maſter;) which <hi>Two</hi> ſhips were carried to <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> That they have made very many preſſing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances for releaſe of the ſaid <hi>Two ſhips,</hi> but could obtaine nothing, onely it was permitted them to make an <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> ſo that the ſaid <hi>Intereſſed</hi> to obtain their <hi>releaſe,</hi> were conſtrained to pay the <hi>ſumm</hi> of 5277. <hi>Livres,</hi> 3. <hi>Solz,</hi> of which they demand <hi>Restitution,</hi> with <hi>Indempnity,</hi> for the reſt of their <hi>ſhips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelus Olpherſen,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Enchuyſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 55.</note> Complains that in the Year, 1655. a ſhip of his named the <hi>Arms of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48101:35"/>Nimmegen,</hi> of which <hi>Richard Trexe</hi> of <hi>Enchuyſen</hi> was <hi>Maſter,</hi> coming from <hi>Roüen</hi> laden with <hi>French Goods,</hi> was taken in the <hi>Channel,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh Captain</hi> (one <hi>Green.</hi>) That the <hi>Goods</hi> were declared <hi>Prize,</hi> but with expreſs condition that the <hi>freight</hi> ſhould be paid to the <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>ſhip:</hi> And though in purſuance thereof, he ought to have received the ſaid <hi>freight,</hi> and to be put into the condition he was in before he was taken, as to his <hi>Cordage, Anchors, Sails, Cables,</hi> and other <hi>neceſſaries</hi> of his <hi>ſhip,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and his men had taken from him; yet ſo it is, that after a great deal of <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>ſolicitation,</hi> and <hi>expence,</hi> he never recovered more then 2000 <hi>Florens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 55. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> We ſay that the <hi>Complaynant</hi> had his <hi>freight adjudged</hi> him; and if it were not <hi>fully paid</hi> him, why did he <hi>accept</hi> of leſs, without <hi>appealing</hi> to the <hi>Court,</hi> who would have ſeen their own <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> fully <hi>executed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gerard Seager,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe <hi>Art.</hi> 56.</note> 
                  <hi>Burgomaſter</hi> of <hi>Enchuyſen</hi> and his <hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates, Owners</hi> of, and <hi>intereſſed</hi> in the ſhip called <hi>the Fortune,</hi> do ſay, That the ſaid ſhip departing from the <hi>Texel</hi> on the 16 of <hi>December,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See this Anſw <hi>p. 60.</hi>
                  </note> 1659. was about <hi>two days</hi> after met at Sea, and fallen foul upon by <hi>two other ſhips</hi> near the <hi>Iſle of Wight;</hi> ſo that being very <hi>Leaky</hi> and unfit to purſue her Voyage, ſhe was conſtrained to put into the <hi>firſt Harbour;</hi> and for avoiding preſent danger, took her Courſe for <hi>Weymouth</hi> in <hi>Portland,</hi> where being arrived in the <hi>Road,</hi> ſhe caſt Anchor, with intent to ſend out one to ask leave of the <hi>Governour</hi> before ſhe entred the <hi>Port.</hi> Whereupon the 20. of <hi>December,</hi> in the <hi>morning,</hi> three <hi>Engliſh Veſſels</hi> came directly to her; <hi>One</hi> of which was Commanded by Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Peter Morell,</hi> who without having received any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, took her, pillaged her, and brought her to <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk:</hi> where the <hi>Aſſociates</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Captain</hi> plundred her of all that was left, as <hi>Victuals, Cordage,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:48101:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Symon Semeynſse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>Burgomaſter</hi> of the ſaid Town of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuyſen,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſiciates</hi> ſay that in <hi>September</hi> 1659. a ſhip of theirs ſerving in the <hi>Herring fiſhing,</hi> called the <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, (John Arentſen, Maſter)</hi> coming from the <hi>Fiſhery,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with about 44 <hi>Tun</hi> of <hi>Salt Herrings,</hi> and 10 <hi>Tun</hi> of <hi>Freſh Herrings,</hi> was attacqued and taken at Sea, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Yarmouth</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh man of War,</hi> called <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Simmons.</hi> That the ſame <hi>Man of War</hi> having taken out of the ſaid ſhip all the ſaid <hi>Herrings,</hi> both <hi>freſh</hi> and <hi>ſalt;</hi> as alſo all the <hi>Sails</hi> and <hi>Cordage;</hi> after he had kept the ſaid <hi>Maſter</hi> in <hi>Arreſt</hi> 7 <hi>Moneths,</hi> ſo that he was utterly ruined; he conſtrained him to come to a <hi>Compoſition,</hi> and to oblige himſelf by the interpoſition on of one <hi>John Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to pay him the ſumm of 21 7 <hi>Florens,</hi> 2 <hi>Solz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 57. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>57.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Complainant</hi> confeſſeth he <hi>compounded</hi> with the <hi>Captain,</hi> and <hi>voluntarily agreed</hi> by the <hi>interpoſition</hi> of his <hi>own friend,</hi> and therefore can have no cauſe for <hi>complaint</hi> of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> done him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heerge Peters Molenear,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 58.</note> dwelling at <hi>Enchuyſen,</hi> do ſay, that one of their ſhips called the <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill,</hi> of which <hi>Peter Corneliſsen</hi> was <hi>Commander</hi> being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Greenland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See this Anſw. <hi>p. 65.</hi>
                  </note> was diſcovered the 6 of <hi>July</hi> 1662. far enough to the <hi>North</hi> from the remoteſt point of any part of the Coaſt, and 24 <hi>Leagues</hi> at leaſt from the <hi>Bay Diſco,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh Fregat</hi> named the <hi>Mary,</hi> of which <hi>John Clarke</hi> was <hi>Captain.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Captain</hi> obliged the ſaid Commander to come aboard him, where he kept him <hi>Priſoner</hi> 3 <hi>days</hi> and <hi>nights,</hi> without any reaſon, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the <hi>inſtances, intreaties,</hi> and <hi>deſires,</hi> of the ſaid Commander.</p>
               <p>That after this the ſaid <hi>Captain</hi> carried the ſaid <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> in his ſhip toward the <hi>Bay,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral</hi> lay, and would not diſmiſs him until he had taken
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48101:36"/>from him by force 4 <hi>Shallops,</hi> 12 <hi>Fiſhing Lines,</hi> 20 <hi>Nets,</hi> 8. <hi>Harpons,</hi> 4 <hi>Shallop ſails,</hi> and all the <hi>Oars,</hi> and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for the whole <hi>Whale fiſhing,</hi> which caſt him into ſuch diſorder, that in the moſt proper ſeaſon of the <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> he was conſtrained to abandon it, and return home.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelius Peterſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Lowen,</hi> and <hi>Peter Adrianſon Van Ley,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Purmerent,</hi> do repreſent that one of their ſhips, named <hi>the Wooden Fort,</hi> on the 2 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1662. being <hi>fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Whales</hi> about 5 or 6 <hi>Leagues</hi> from the <hi>Coaſt</hi> toward the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Belſont,</hi> and having the day before taken a <hi>Whale 16 Leagues</hi> from <hi>Land,</hi> was attacqued by 2 <hi>Engliſh Veſſels</hi> of which <hi>one</hi> was a <hi>Fregat</hi> commanded by Captain <hi>John Clark</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> a <hi>Pinnace,</hi> of which <hi>John Piper</hi> was <hi>Captain,</hi> and after they had committed ſeveral out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages upon him, he was carried by them into the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Belſont</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Admiral, John Mandrey;</hi> and though the ſaid <hi>Admiral</hi> could not pretend any <hi>right</hi> to the <hi>Whale</hi> that had been taken; and confeſſed he had nothing to pretend to it, if it were taken 14 or 15 <hi>Leagues</hi> from the <hi>Coaſt;</hi> and notwithſtanding all the <hi>Mariners</hi> of the <hi>ſhip</hi> the <hi>Wooden Fort,</hi> did declare that it was taken at that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, yet the ſaid <hi>Admiral</hi> did not onely take the ſaid <hi>Whale,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Finns</hi> of another; 2 <hi>Shallops,</hi> 12 <hi>Lines,</hi> 24 <hi>Oars,</hi> 24 <hi>Nets,</hi> 4 <hi>Harpons,</hi> and many other <hi>Inſtruments</hi> neceſſary both for <hi>Fiſhing</hi> and <hi>Navigation;</hi> ſo that the ſaid ſhip finding her ſelf by that means diſabled to continue her <hi>fiſhery,</hi> the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> have reaſon to demand <hi>reparation</hi> for their <hi>damages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jacob Jeuniſsen Winding</hi> and his <hi>Aſsociates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 60.</note> do ſay, That on the 3 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1662. one of their ſhips named the <hi>Prince William,</hi> of which <hi>William Jacobſon</hi> was <hi>Commander,</hi> being <hi>fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Whales</hi> in <hi>Greenland,</hi> the ſaid ſhip was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by a ſmall Wind near to <hi>Belſont,</hi> within 5 or 6 <hi>Leagues</hi> of the <hi>Coaſt;</hi> and there met Captain <hi>John Clark</hi> in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with another fair <hi>Engliſh ſhip, well mounted.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48101:36"/>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>John Clark</hi> did firſt make a <hi>ſhot over him,</hi> and then <hi>Another</hi> directly <hi>At</hi> him, and ſo forced the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> to come aboard him. And while the ſaid <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was <hi>aboard</hi> the ſaid <hi>Fregat,</hi> with ſome of his <hi>Seamen,</hi> the men of the <hi>Fregat</hi> entred the <hi>ſhip Prince William,</hi> and took out of her by force, as follows, 2 <hi>Shallops,</hi> 18 <hi>Lines,</hi> 23 <hi>Nets,</hi> 10 <hi>Harpons,</hi> 10 <hi>Foregangers,</hi> 20 <hi>Oars,</hi> 2 <hi>Sails,</hi> 4 <hi>Hatchets,</hi> 1 <hi>ſlitting Knife,</hi> and other <hi>Inſtruments;</hi> and moreover, the <hi>Captain</hi> extorted from him for his <hi>two ſhot</hi> which he had made, 20 <hi>Florens</hi> in <hi>money,</hi> 4 <hi>Cheeſes,</hi> 2 <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of Brandy,</hi> and a <hi>bag</hi> of <hi>Grout;</hi> ſo the ſaid <hi>Commander</hi> being by reaſon of this <hi>pillage,</hi> put out of all condition to continue his <hi>fiſhing,</hi> was conſtrained to return home.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Claeſsen, Merchant</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> dwelling in the <hi>Ryp,</hi> do complain, That one of their ſhips named the <hi>Fiſher,</hi> of which <hi>John Ariſsen Brack</hi> was <hi>Commander,</hi> being in <hi>June</hi> 1662. arrived in <hi>Greenland</hi> to <hi>fiſh</hi> for <hi>Whales,</hi> had there the ill luck to receive ſuch damage and diſorder by the <hi>Ice,</hi> that to <hi>ſtop</hi> his <hi>Leaks,</hi> and <hi>caulk</hi> his <hi>ſhip,</hi> he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to draw near the <hi>Coast;</hi> and in purſuit thereof, the ſaid <hi>Commander</hi> the 26 of the ſaid <hi>Moneth,</hi> entred with his ſhip into the ſaid <hi>Harbour,</hi> called <hi>Green-Hauberg,</hi> in <hi>Spits-Bergen,</hi> and cauſed his ſhip to be there <hi>Carined,</hi> to <hi>ſtop</hi> her <hi>Leaks;</hi> where the ſaid ſhip being thus repaired, and ready to return to the <hi>fiſhing,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Captain John Clark</hi> came directly upon him, and took from him 4 <hi>Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops,</hi> 9 <hi>Lines,</hi> 15 <hi>Nets,</hi> 24 <hi>Oars,</hi> ſome <hi>Sails,</hi> and <hi>Maſts,</hi> a great quantity of <hi>Hatchets,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Knives</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils</hi> neceſſary for <hi>fiſhing;</hi> ſo that by this means the ſaid <hi>Commander</hi> found himſelf diſabled to continue the <hi>fiſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 58, 59, and 60. <hi>Article,</hi> It is anſwered;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſwer to</hi> 58, 59, 60.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That the Country of <hi>Greenland</hi> was <hi>diſcovered</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> about the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> his raign, the <hi>Kings Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:48101:37"/>was <hi>ſet up,</hi> and the <hi>dominion thereof aſſumed</hi> to be in His Majeſty, by the name of King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>New-Land:</hi> in purſuance whereof, his ſaid Majeſty did by ſeveral <hi>Acts of State,</hi> aſſert his <hi>right</hi> thereunto; and particularly the 10. of <hi>January</hi> 1613. his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was ſignified unto Sr. <hi>Noel Caroon</hi> Knight, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour</hi> for the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> as followeth; <hi>viz.</hi> That the ſaid Country of <hi>Greenland,</hi> together with the <hi>fiſhing</hi> of <hi>Whales</hi> upon that <hi>Coaſt,</hi> and all other <hi>Commodities</hi> ariſing from <hi>thence,</hi> do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to his <hi>Majeſty, Jure Dominii,</hi> His <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> having been the <hi>firſt diſcoverers</hi> thereof, as was made manifeſt unto the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Majeſties Privy Council;</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> taken in the <hi>name,</hi> and on the <hi>behalf</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by erecting his <hi>Highneſſes Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> on that place, and therefore that without leave firſt obtained from his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> or from thoſe to whom his <hi>Highneſs</hi> had granted the ſole uſe and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion thereof, it is not <hi>lawful</hi> for any other of his <hi>Majesties Subjects</hi> (much leſs for <hi>Strangers</hi>) to fiſh or abide there: And whoſoever ſhould preſume to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any ſuch thing, (as it appeared the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had done) eſpecially being forewarned as they had been the year before) if thereupon any prejudice or loſs did happen unto them, either in their perſons, or goods, by being forc'd to depart, or having their Commodities taken from them, they cannot juſtly complain of any wrong, for they came thither upon their own perils.</p>
               <p>And in purfuance of their <hi>Right,</hi> his <hi>Then Majeſty</hi> and King <hi>Charles the Firſt,</hi> of bleſſed Memory, and their Subjects, by their Authority, having conſtantly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and maintained the <hi>fiſhing</hi> in <hi>Bell Sound, Green
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48101:37"/>Harbour,</hi> and the <hi>Harbours</hi> and <hi>places</hi> adjacent, againſt all Nations which have intruded, and in particular, in the year 1618. in the defence and exerciſe of this Right, therein the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſuſtained great <hi>damages,</hi> to the value of 66436 <hi>pounds</hi> 15 <hi>ſhillings,</hi> by the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Zealanders;</hi> the doing whereof was diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>States,</hi> as a <hi>depredation,</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon by <hi>Commiſſioners;</hi> who not agreeing, it was referred to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> who awarded 22000 <hi>pounds</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Merchants,</hi> but no part thereof was ever paid: And as a farther teſtimony of their <hi>Right</hi> by <hi>Occupancy,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are the onely perſons that ever did <hi>Winter</hi> there.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> to render this Right as ineffectual as they could, have oftentimes of <hi>late years</hi> ridden with their <hi>ſhips</hi> before the ſaid <hi>Harbours,</hi> to diſturb the <hi>fiſhing</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> and diverting the <hi>Whales</hi> from <hi>coming in:</hi> To prevent which, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have to their great trouble and damage, been compelled to leave their <hi>fiſhing</hi> in the <hi>Harbours,</hi> and come forth to warn them away, both by fair means, and by force; which <hi>warning</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> have ever uſed to receive, and to ſubmit to the <hi>Engliſh right</hi> by their <hi>departure</hi> accordingly; but no damage was ever heretofore pretended for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, in the Year 1660, and 1661. the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the <hi>United Netherlands</hi> growing more <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous</hi> and <hi>inſolent</hi> upon that <hi>Coaſt,</hi> complaint thereof being made to his <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>York, Lord High Admiral</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> his ſaid <hi>Highneſs</hi> was pleaſed in the Year 1662. to ſend Captain <hi>John Clark</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:48101:38"/>with one of his Majeſties <hi>Veſſels</hi> called the <hi>Little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> to protect the <hi>fiſhing;</hi> who in order thereunto, did warn the <hi>Dutch</hi> off from that <hi>Coast,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> uſed to <hi>fiſh,</hi> and have right of <hi>fiſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>particulars</hi> mentioned; We anſwer, that Captain <hi>Clark,</hi> and the others named therein, being <hi>Mariners</hi> and <hi>abroad</hi> upon their ſeveral <hi>employments,</hi> full anſwer cannot be given thereunto; but certain it is, that <hi>no claim</hi> hath hitherto been made by any perſon whatſoever in any of his <hi>Majeſties Courts</hi> of <hi>juſtice,</hi> nor <hi>demand</hi> elſewhere; which gives juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to conclude that all thoſe <hi>complaints</hi> are groundleſs.</p>
               <p>All that we can hear of is, That <hi>two ſhips</hi> of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> riding in one of the <hi>Engliſh Harbours,</hi> called <hi>Fair Fore-land, alias,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Smiths Bay,</hi> contrary to order before given by the aforeſaid Cap. <hi>Clark,</hi> were by him forced to depart: from whom he took only 5 <hi>Shallops,</hi> with ſome other <hi>fiſhing inſtruments,</hi> whereby to diſable them from farther diſturbance of <hi>fiſhing</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Harbours,</hi> which could not be much <hi>damage</hi> unto them, the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> for <hi>fiſhing</hi> at <hi>Sea</hi> (which was their deſign) being then paſt.</p>
               <p>For the ſhip called the <hi>Wooden Fort,</hi> from which it is ſaid there was a <hi>Whale</hi> taken, it is affirmed, that ſhe was riding within <hi>two Leagues</hi> of <hi>Bell point,</hi> in the <hi>mouth</hi> of the Harbour, which is a place proper to do miſchief to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>ſcaring</hi> and diverting the <hi>Whales,</hi> but not <hi>fit</hi> to <hi>fiſh</hi> in, and the ſaid <hi>Captain Clark</hi> coming <hi>on board,</hi> and finding a <hi>Whale</hi> newly killed, cauſed the ſaid <hi>Whale,</hi> as alſo 2 <hi>Shallops</hi> to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48101:38"/>be taken from him; being there in contempt of his <hi>Majeſties Authority</hi> after warning given, and in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of his <hi>Highneſs Commiſſion:</hi> But the ſaid ſhip had in her <hi>Hold</hi> to the quantity of 5 or 6 <hi>Whales</hi> in <hi>Bubber,</hi> and <hi>Einns,</hi> which he did not meddle withall, conceiving them to have been taken at <hi>Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>fourth ſhip,</hi> for the reaſons aforeſaid, no particular accompt can be given thereof; but by all that is alleaged, it appears that Captain <hi>Clark</hi> onely took from her ſuch <hi>Utenſils,</hi> as might diſable them from <hi>fiſhing in</hi> or <hi>before</hi> the <hi>Harbour,</hi> to the <hi>disturbance</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> which His <hi>Majeſties Subjects</hi> hold themſelves bound to <hi>defend,</hi> ſo long as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall pleaſe to <hi>aſſert</hi> his <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> and <hi>right</hi> of <hi>fiſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Johnſon Kreigt,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Graft,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 61.</note> That one of his ſhips <hi>fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Herrings;</hi> named the <hi>Charity,</hi> (<hi>Martin Geritzen</hi> Maſters Mate) returning from <hi>fiſhing,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with 21 Laſt of Herrings;<note place="margin" type="runSum">See for the Anſwer to the <hi>61, 62, 63, &amp; 64.</hi> in <hi>pag. 60.</hi>
                  </note> and having withal 120 Livres in <hi>money,</hi> which he had received for a <hi>Laſt</hi> of <hi>Herrings</hi> that he had ſold, was upon the 13. of <hi>September</hi> 1661. attacqued about 8 <hi>Leagues</hi> from the <hi>Texel,</hi> and taken by one Captain <hi>Sadlington,</hi> and carried to <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> where being arrived, the ſaid Maſters Mate ſaw his ſhip unladen, and was afterwards conſtrained to carry her to <hi>Weſnoo,</hi> where he was forced to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas-Corſſen</hi> of <hi>Adrichen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 62.</note> Burgomaſter of the Town of <hi>Vlaerding,</hi> complains that one of his ſhips named the <hi>Creſcent;</hi> of which <hi>Henry Baſtiaens</hi> was Maſters Mate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48101:39"/>laden with 14 Laſts of <hi>Herrings,</hi> was in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1659. taken by Captain <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Newcastle,</hi> whoſe <hi>Aſſociates</hi> (as the ſaid <hi>Nicholas Corſſen</hi> is informed) dwelt at <hi>Leith</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aaron de Voſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 63.</note> Burgomaſter of the ſame Town, ſaith that one of his ſhips <hi>fiſhing</hi> for <hi>Herring,</hi> named the <hi>Fox,</hi> of which <hi>Joſeph Foppen</hi> was Maſter, being departed with many other Veſſels for the ſaid <hi>Fiſhery,</hi> and being laden with 285 <hi>Barrels</hi> and a <hi>half</hi> of <hi>Herring,</hi> was taken the 11 of <hi>July</hi> 1660. by the above named Captain <hi>Geo. Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> of <hi>Leith</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> whither the ſhip being brought, the ſaid <hi>Aaron de Voſſe</hi> took a great deal of pains, and made great ſolicitation for the <hi>Restitution</hi> of his <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Goods,</hi> as alſo for the reparation of <hi>damages</hi> ſuffered by him, but notwithſtanding all his pains and ſolicitatious, he could not obtain the <hi>restitution</hi> of one <hi>penny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Martenſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 64.</note> 
                  <hi>Olden Roggen, Schepen</hi> of the ſame Town, complains, That a ſhip of his, of the burden of 54 <hi>Tun</hi> being gone to Sea to <hi>fiſh,</hi> and being upon the 13 of <hi>April</hi> 1659. about 3 <hi>Leagues</hi> to the <hi>Northwards</hi> of the <hi>Sables,</hi> was attacqued, taken, and carried to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> by a Captain called <hi>John of London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Andrieſen</hi> formerly Maſter of the ſhip called the St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 65.</note> doth complain, That being departed from <hi>Middleburgh</hi> in <hi>Zealand</hi> the 18. of <hi>December</hi> 1661. armed with a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from the <hi>States</hi> to go to the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> was taken and pillaged 10 <hi>Leagues</hi> from <hi>Cape de Cruze,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Cuba,</hi> by a <hi>Captain</hi> named <hi>James Young,</hi> who had fitted his ſhip at <hi>London,</hi> and had his retreat in the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Jamaica;</hi> which <hi>Prize</hi> was taken the 24. of <hi>May</hi> 1662. and from the ſhip which was pillaged there was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and carried away, (beſides what the <hi>Seamen</hi> took) all the <hi>Cargazon</hi> and <hi>Merchandize</hi> that had been entruſted with the Maſter of the ſaid ſhip, to trade withal; ſo that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48101:39"/>they <hi>find</hi> themſelves well warranted to demand ſatisfaction by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Original Factors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 65. <hi>Article;</hi> We ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 65.</note> that no ſuch man had any <hi>Commiſsion</hi> from <hi>Jamaica;</hi> but we have heard that ſuch a perſon had obtained a <hi>Portugal Commiſsion,</hi> and did <hi>Plunder Engliſh Ships,</hi> and all Veſſels that he took; but durſt never go into <hi>Jamaica</hi> for that <hi>Colonel Doyly,</hi> the <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>That Place,</hi> gave Orders to all <hi>Men of War</hi> to apprehend him, for his <hi>Inſolence</hi> to a Veſſel called, <hi>The Bleſſing of London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelius de Lincourt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 66.</note> hath preſented to their Lordſhips a <hi>memorial</hi> of <hi>Goods,</hi> that his Father <hi>Jacob de Lincourt</hi> decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, left in the <hi>Iſland of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1655, which have been detained by him that commands for the King of <hi>England</hi> in the ſame <hi>Iſland;</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe, <hi>that there ought to be a recovery made upon them, for the loſses which the</hi> Engliſh <hi>pretend to have ſuffered by the ſaid</hi> Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius de Lincourt <hi>during the late War with</hi> England; <hi>becauſe he had taken ſome of their Buildings:</hi> And foraſmuch as the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners</hi> eſtabliſhed over the ſaid goods, to wit, <hi>Captain Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Treſilgem, Captain Samuel Wintrym,</hi> and <hi>Maſter William Jordan,</hi> have declared that the <hi>Goods</hi> of the deceaſed are in <hi>their cuſtody;</hi> and of what <hi>Value</hi> they are, according to the accompt of <hi>Sugars,</hi> and <hi>Indico,</hi> which they have Eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at 306100<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. of <hi>Sugar,</hi> and 750<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. of <hi>Indico,</hi> he demands <hi>Reſtitution</hi> with <hi>Indemnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 66. <hi>Article;</hi> If the <hi>complainant</hi> have <hi>Right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 66.</note> he muſt ſeek it upon the <hi>Iſland,</hi> by courſe of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and his <hi>pretence</hi> ought not to be admitted againſt <hi>our Nation</hi> untill <hi>that</hi> be <hi>denyed</hi> Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leonard Johnſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 67.</note> formerly Maſter of the ſhip called the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48101:40"/>
                  <hi>Martin of Roſſum,</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> hath repreſented to the <hi>States</hi> an <hi>Authentick Copy Tranſlated</hi> out of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> being in effect, a Declaration of the <hi>Governour</hi> for the KING of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> by which it is teſtified that the ſaid <hi>Leonard Johnſon</hi> Arrived the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1661. in that <hi>Harbour,</hi> with his <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Company,</hi> in a miſerable condition, having no more money then 50. <hi>Ryalls of Eight,</hi> to ſupply their neceſſities, he therefore obtained leave to fell 30 <hi>Negroes;</hi> but afterwards deſiring leave to ſell all the reſt of the <hi>Negroes</hi> he had, it was refuſed him, and he had his <hi>Paſs-port</hi> to be gone: But notwithſtanding, after his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from thence, the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> 1662. he returned thither again, by miſchance, <hi>two dayes after,</hi> and was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>Borded</hi> by ſome <hi>Seamen</hi> belonging to his <hi>Majeſties Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat,</hi> called the <hi>Diamond,</hi> commanded by <hi>Captain Richard Whiting,</hi> according to the Inſtructions of his <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>York, Lord High Admiral of England:</hi> But the <hi>Governour</hi> having put all under a <hi>Guard,</hi> cauſed the <hi>ſhip</hi> to be <hi>viſited,</hi> and finding that the ſaid <hi>Leonard Johnſon</hi> in the <hi>ſale</hi> of his <hi>Negroes,</hi> had not exceeded the <hi>Number</hi> that was allowed him, and becauſe there was no more found in his ſhip then 260. <hi>pound,</hi> of which 218. <hi>pounds</hi> was carried to the <hi>Governour,</hi> and 50. <hi>Negroes,</hi> who were rated at 478. <hi>pounds sterling,</hi> which <hi>ſumm</hi> being added to the 218. <hi>pounds,</hi> makes in all the <hi>ſumm</hi> of 696. <hi>pounds sterling,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Governour</hi> did remin to his <hi>Royall Highneſs,</hi> or to his <hi>Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 67. <hi>Article;</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 67.</note> The <hi>Admiſsion</hi> of the <hi>complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants Ship</hi> firſt to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> was a noble exceſs of <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in the <hi>Governour,</hi> who took upon him to diſpence with the <hi>Law,</hi> to <hi>ſupply</hi> the <hi>complainants</hi> needs; That the taking of the ſhip <hi>afterwards,</hi> was what the <hi>Captain might,</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to do by <hi>Law,</hi> and his <hi>Duty;</hi> And if the <hi>complainant</hi> had any thing <hi>restored</hi> him, he owes <hi>thanks</hi> for that, and ought not to <hi>complain,</hi> that a <hi>part</hi> was <hi>detained,</hi> when the <hi>whole</hi> was <hi>Legally conſiſcable</hi> for
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48101:40"/>his <hi>trading</hi> with <hi>our Plantations, contrary</hi> to the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Navigation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> in the <hi>ſhip</hi> named the S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 68.</note> of which <hi>Leven Kachlaer</hi> of <hi>Trevere</hi> in <hi>Zealand</hi> was Maſter, do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> departing from <hi>Trevere</hi> in the <hi>month</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1662. Bound for <hi>France,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">See this Anſw. <hi>p. 60.</hi>
                  </note> was met near the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by a <hi>Fregat</hi> Commanded by <hi>Captain Jacob Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaber,</hi> who made himſelf <hi>master of the ſaid ſhip</hi> on the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1662. and carried <hi>her</hi> to <hi>Rye</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is further repreſented, that <hi>Bartholomew de Jager,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 69.</note> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> Maſter of the ſhip called the <hi>Fortune,</hi> (a <hi>Veſſell</hi> of 150. <hi>Tun,</hi> or thereabouts) departed form <hi>Middleburgh, April</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1652. with the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>lading,</hi> confiſting of 450. <hi>Quintalls</hi> (<hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>France</hi>) of <hi>ſalt,</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Martin. Twelve</hi> pieces of <hi>Aquavitae</hi> of <hi>Rochel,</hi> which were laden at <hi>Rochel,</hi> by <hi>Chriſtian Denis,</hi> and <hi>Maquet,</hi> and belonging (as it appears by the <hi>Bills of Lading</hi>) to <hi>Regnier Martenſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob Lievens, Merchants</hi> of <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> to go for <hi>Nieuport;</hi> and that being Arriv'd upon the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the ſame <hi>moneth,</hi> before the <hi>Harbour</hi> of that <hi>Town,</hi> at break of day he came to an Anchour, and that early in the morning, <hi>Three ſhips</hi> of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> came up directly to him, namely <hi>Two</hi> of the <hi>ſquadron</hi> of <hi>Vice-Admiral Goodſon,</hi> who lay before <hi>Ost-end,</hi> and the <hi>third</hi> coming from the <hi>West,</hi> who approaching the ſaid <hi>Veſſel,</hi> made ſeveral ſhot at her, ſo that the <hi>Maſter,</hi> and his men were fain to leave the <hi>ſhip</hi> to ſave their lives; having firſt nailed his <hi>Sea-brief</hi> to the <hi>main-mast,</hi> to ſhew that both <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> were <hi>free.</hi> He did alſo cauſe to be planted a <hi>white flagg,</hi> joyning with it <hi>One</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi>'s, to notifie that all was <hi>free;</hi> But this ſignified lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, although the ſaid <hi>Lievens</hi> had alſo given to underſtand that the <hi>ſhip</hi> was his; for the <hi>men</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Parliament Veſſel</hi> came up notwithſtanding with their <hi>Shallops</hi> to the ſaid <hi>ſhip</hi> the <hi>Fortune,</hi> under <hi>protection</hi> of their <hi>Cannon,</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48101:41"/>took away <hi>Anchors, Cordage, Sails, Cable,</hi> &amp;c. and ſet fire at laſt both to <hi>ſhip</hi> and <hi>lading.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the 69. <hi>Article,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer <hi>69.</hi>
                  </note> we ſay, That <hi>Vice-Admiral Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Commanded no <hi>Squadron</hi> of <hi>Ships</hi> in the Year, 1662. and therefore if any thing was done of what is <hi>complained</hi> at that time, it muſt be done by ſome other <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieroſme Corneliſſen</hi> of <hi>Fluſhing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Art.</hi> 70.</note> declareth likewiſe, that he departed from <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> on the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1657. under the <hi>Convoy</hi> of <hi>John Thyſſen</hi> for <hi>Ostend,</hi> laden with <hi>bay-ſalt;</hi> and that about two Leagues from the Town of <hi>Ostend,</hi> two <hi>Fregats</hi> came up to him, the one Commanded by <hi>Captain Lambert,</hi> and the other by <hi>Captain Groff,</hi> the latter of which <hi>pillaged</hi> him: But however the ſaid <hi>Captain</hi> promiſing that he would reſtore the whole to him,<note place="margin" type="runSum">See for the Anſwer to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes <hi>70, 71, 72.</hi> in <hi>pa. 60.</hi>
                  </note> provided he would give him a <hi>Declaration</hi> that he had not been <hi>damnified</hi> by him; which the ſaid <hi>Corneliſſen</hi> conſented to; but after the giving thereof, he could get no more of him then <hi>nine Livres de gros:</hi> His loſſe amounting (beſides that) to 13 <hi>Livres,</hi> 16 <hi>Solz,</hi> and 9 <hi>Deniers de gros;</hi> and that of his man to four <hi>Livres de gros,</hi> of which he could not obtain <hi>Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the <hi>Intereſſed</hi> in the 19 <hi>ſhips</hi> that went from <hi>Fluſhing</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>August,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Arti.</hi> 71.</note> 1656. under the <hi>Convoy</hi> of <hi>Captain John Tyſon,</hi> do repreſent that the ſaid <hi>ſhips</hi> being Arrived near <hi>Blanckenburgh,</hi> did there meet 6 or 7 <hi>Engliſh Veſſels,</hi> who <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqued</hi> them, being laden with <hi>Wine, Brandy</hi> and <hi>Salt,</hi> and fired upon them furiouſly, took and ſunk 5 or 6, ſo that there Arrived at <hi>Ostend</hi> but 13, or 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelius Janſſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Anti.</hi> 72.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter Bogart, John Andreeſſen,</hi> Maſters of <hi>ſhips</hi> dwelling at <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> and <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> do <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> That ſailing in the Year, 1659. with their <hi>ſhips</hi> and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48101:41"/>
                  <hi>Merchandizes</hi> which were not <hi>Contrabanda,</hi> towards <hi>Oſtend,</hi> were driven back by certain ſhips in ſuch manner, that they were conſtrained to return to the place from whence they departed, and where they were <hi>freighted</hi> which did them a great deal of <hi>wrong,</hi> and they have reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to be <hi>Indemnified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſhip named the <hi>Town and Country Adjacent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pretenſe. <hi>Artic.</hi> 73.</note> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Weſt India Company of the Chamber of Groninghen,</hi> was taken by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the <hi>Channel,</hi> with the <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes</hi> thereunto belonging, <hi>and Depending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we know the <hi>Captain</hi> that <hi>took</hi> her,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. <hi>73.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>time when,</hi> and <hi>where</hi> any <hi>claim</hi> hath formerly been <hi>made, an Anſwer ſhall be given.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
